<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spiritual vvorship exalted. Or A treatise concerning the worship and service of God shewing how uncapable men are in their natural and unconverted state of worshipping and serving God acceptably in this Gospel day. And that it is the light, grace and spirit of Christ revealed in men, which doth renew, fit, prepare and [q]ualifie them for performing that pure spiritual and acceptable worship which was instituted by our Lord, and practiced by his disciples and followers. As also several other things here inserted, worthy of observation. By a lover of truth, and wel-wisher of the souls of all men, George Myers.</title>
            <author>Myers, George, 1653?-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3174</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213894</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826149</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30541</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51669)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30541)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1799:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spiritual vvorship exalted. Or A treatise concerning the worship and service of God shewing how uncapable men are in their natural and unconverted state of worshipping and serving God acceptably in this Gospel day. And that it is the light, grace and spirit of Christ revealed in men, which doth renew, fit, prepare and [q]ualifie them for performing that pure spiritual and acceptable worship which was instituted by our Lord, and practiced by his disciples and followers. As also several other things here inserted, worthy of observation. By a lover of truth, and wel-wisher of the souls of all men, George Myers.</title>
                  <author>Myers, George, 1653?-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 102 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Messiahship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30541:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Spiritual Worſhip EXALTED.</p>
            <p>OR A <hi>Treatiſe</hi> concerning the <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> Shewing how uncapable men are in their natural and unconverted State of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping and Serving God acceptably in this Goſpel day.</p>
            <p>And that it is the Light, Grace and Spirit of Chriſt reveaved in men, which doth Renew, Fit, Prepare and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ualifie them for performing that Pure Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Acceptable Worſhip which was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Lord, and practiced by his Diſciples and Followers. As alſo ſeveral other things here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, worthy of obſervation.</p>
            <p>By a Lover of Truth, and Wel-wiſher of the Souls of all men, <hi>George Myers.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs unto him, neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritualy diſcern'd</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 2.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth, for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 4.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 4.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Give unto the Lord the Glory due unto his Name. Worſhip the Lord in the Beauty of Holineſs,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 29.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:30541:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30541:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> is the ſupream act of mans Life, and a duty incumbent upon all; for that thereby we anſwer the end of our <hi>Creation,</hi> and pay thoſe Reſpects and Acknowledgments which we owe to the <hi>Divine Majeſty,</hi> for all his Bounties and Favours towards us: It greatly behoves all People to be very ſerious and weighty in that reſpect, and truly to inform themſelves what that Worſhip is which is acceptable unto God, and how People ought to be qualified for performing the ſame;
<pb facs="tcp:30541:3"/>the want of a right underſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe accounts has occaſioned great Miſcarriages and Defects among People in <hi>Religions matters</hi> and is one great reaſon why there are ſo many Jars and Diviſions about the ſeveral Forms and Ways of Worſhip now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration of theſe things, together with the drawings of Divine Love, have induced me to the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this following <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> wherein divers things relating to the Worſhip and Service of God are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and held forth, and whereby it is manifeſt that it is the Light, Grace and Spirit of Chriſt, revealed in the Hearts of the Sons and Daughters of Men, that rightly Renews, Fits, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares and Qualifies them for Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and Serving God acceptably, and opens their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings in Divine and Spiritual matters, inſomuch that in all acts of Worſhip and Service un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is to have
<pb facs="tcp:30541:3"/>the Precedency, ſo as to move, act, influence and aſſiſt the Perſons exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed therein, whether it be in publick Preaching, Teſtimonies and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Truth,</hi> or in Prayers, Praiſes and Thankſgivings unto him.</p>
            <p>And alſo that thoſe who in their own Will and Time do go about to perform acts of Worſhip and Service unto God, in their Natural and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted State, whilſt they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing and diſ-regarding the Counſel, Drawings and Directions of the Light and Spirit of Chriſt in themſelves; ſuch Worſhippers, in that State, and under thoſe Circumſtances, may pleaſe themſelves with ſuch pretences; but can no way perform that Divine and Spiritual Worſhip which is acceptable unto God in this Goſpel day.</p>
            <p>Although, I might have produced divers Teſtimonies, both of Antient and Modern <hi>Authors,</hi> in favour of this <hi>Diſcourſe;</hi> yet for ſeveral Reaſons,
<pb facs="tcp:30541:4"/>I rather chuſe to keep cloſe to the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> inaſmuch as I conceive thoſe who are inclined to be Religious will not dare to make excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt that which is concluded to proceed from the Divine Spirit.</p>
            <p>Let none be Offended that I do not admit of <hi>human Learning,</hi> and <hi>natural Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> to be of ſuch abſolute neceſſity for the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of a <hi>Goſpel Miniſter,</hi> as ſome would have them: For by what is here Written, I do no way in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to undervalue <hi>human Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or leſſen its eſteem in the minds of ſuch as are inclin'd to make a right uſe thereof; for I do grant, that it is good and ſerviceable in its place, yea, it is, and may be ſerviceable upon many accounts to a Goſpel Miniſter, where it is reduc'd to a bleſſed Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination and Conformity to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth; but then if People will attempt to exalt it above the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb facs="tcp:30541:4"/>of the <hi>Divine Spirit,</hi> and lay that ſtreſs upon it for opening the Myſteries of Truth which the Holy Ghoſt will not admit of, in that caſe I found my ſelf concern'd to bear a Teſtimony for the Truth, and againſt the Vanity of ſuch as would extol hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Learning and natural Arts and Sciences above their proper uſe and ſervice.</p>
            <p>Albeit, the conſideration of thoſe many Treatiſes which have been writ, by other Hands, upon theſe accounts, did at firſt ſeem to divert me from this undertaking; yet for clearing of my Conſcience in the ſight of God, and in performance of that Duty and Service which I owe to him, I thought fit to caſt my Mite into the Treaſury, deſiring that what I have here Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Humility,</hi> may be Read and Expounded in <hi>Charity;</hi> and that God Almighty, who is the Author of all our Bleſſings, may by his Grace and Goodneſs make this ſmall <hi>Treatiſe</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30541:5"/>effectual for informing the minds of People upon theſe accounts, and for reducing them into that pure and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Worſhip which is acceptable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So deſireth, and ſo prayeth thy Chriſtian Friend, <hi>George Myers.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:30541:5"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>§. 1. COncerning the Worſhip that was Inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt, and Practiced by his People. <hi>pag.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>§. 2. Concerning Mans incapacity of Worſhiping and Serving God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably in his natural and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted State. <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>§. 3. Concerning the neceſſity of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Light, Grace and Spirit of Chriſt in order to quicken and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new to God, and ſo to prepare and qualifie People for his Worſhip and Service. <hi>pag.</hi> 10.</item>
               <item>§. 4. Concerning the Goſpel Church and Evangelical Temple. <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</item>
               <item>§. 5. Concerning ſilent waiting upon God, for the help and concurrence of his holy Spirit, in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of Divine Worſhip. <hi>pag.</hi> 20.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:30541:6"/>
               <item>§. 6. Concerning the Preparation, Call, and Ordination of Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. <hi>pag.</hi> 25.</item>
               <item>§. 7. Concerning Women Preaching. <hi>pag.</hi> 34.</item>
               <item>§. 8. Concerning the Riſe of Goſpel Performances, &amp; the Qualifications of Goſpel Miniſters, ſhowing that they are not from Human Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Worldly Wiſdom and Natural Arts and Sciences, but from the Divine Spirit. <hi>pag.</hi> 43.</item>
               <item>§. 9. Concerning outward Force and Violence in Religious matters, and the unlawfulneſs of forceable reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the temporal Magiſtracy <hi>p.</hi> 55.</item>
               <item>§. 10. Concerning the Maintenance of Goſpel Miniſters. <hi>pag.</hi> 63.</item>
               <item>§. 11. Concerning Prayer. <hi>pag.</hi> 75.</item>
               <item>§. 12. Concerning Singing of Pſalms, and Artifical Muſick. <hi>pag.</hi> 88.</item>
               <item>The Concluſion. <hi>pag.</hi> 98.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30541:6"/>
            <head>THE Spiritual Worſhip EXALTED.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section I.</hi> Concerning the Worſhip that was Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Jeſus Chriſt, and Practiced by his People.</head>
               <p>AFter the Lord God, in his own appointed time, ſaw meet to put an end to the Diſpenſation of the Law, which was delivered unto the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the Miniſtry of <hi>Moſes;</hi> it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, according to his determinate Will and everlaſting Counſel, to ſend his own Son, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Judea,</hi> of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets did write, and whom <hi>John</hi> teſtified of <hi>to be the Lamb of God who taketh away the Sins of the World,</hi> John 1.29. He perfectly fulfilled the Law, and the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30541:7"/>Righteouſneſs thereof, and gave witneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Diſpenſation of the Goſpel, drawing Religion into the ſecret of the Heart, he made it to conſiſt in a higher ſtate of Righteouſneſs, then that of the Law, called Evangelical; he alſo approved himſelf, and the excellency of his Doctrine, by many great and wonderful Signes and Miracles, and ſealed it with his Blood; for that after he had preach't that heavenly Doctrine, and wrought many Miracles among the <hi>Jews,</hi> he was apprehended, and by wicked hands was Crucified and Slain, yet God raiſed him up again; ſo that he triumphed over Death, of which it was impoſſible for him to be held; and after he was ſo raiſed up from the Dead, he appeared to his Diſciples and Followers, who had believed in him, comforting them with the hope and aſſurance of the pouring forth &amp; attendance of his Spirit, by which he was to be with them unto the end of the World; and by which they, and all ſuch as afterwards ſhould come to believe in his holy Name might be rendered capable of bearing and holding forth a true, certain and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Teſtimony for him whom God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Salvation unto the ends of the Earth, and alſo of performing that Worſhip and Service which was inſtituted by him,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30541:7"/>which Worſhip is Spiritual, and cannot be truly performed by the Art, Strength, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Policy of men in their natural and unconverted ſtate, but only by thoſe who are ſpiritually quickened and renewed unto God (in ſome meaſure) and whoſe Hearts and Souls are fitted and prepared by the Light, Grace, Spirit &amp; Power of our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>That the Worſhip inſtituted by Chriſt is Spiritual is very plain, from his own Words unto the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> John 4.21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>Jeſus ſaid unto her, Woman, believe me, the hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>worſhip the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ye worſhip ye know not what, we know what we worſhip, for Salvation is of the</hi> Jews; <hi>but the hour cometh, and now is, when the true Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth, for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him; God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> This is the chiefeſt and moſt ample Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that Chriſt gives of the Chriſtian worſhip, as different and contradiſtinguiſhed from that under the Law; he tyeth not his People to the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> nor unto any other place, but plainly holds out, that the ſeaſon is now come, wherein the worſhip muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30541:8"/>be in Spirit and in Truth; he alſo gives the reaſon for it, and excellently argues from the anology that ought to be betwixt the Object and the Worſhip directed thereunto, <hi>viz. God is a Spirit, therefore he muſt be worſhipped in Spirit</hi>—This Teſtimony of our Lord is ſo clear in the caſe, that I need not enlarge much further upon it, but only add the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the Church at <hi>Philippi, We are the Circumciſion that worſhip God in the Spirit, and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, having no confidence in the Fleſh,</hi> Phil. 3.3 By which it appears, that the Saints and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, in thoſe dayes, were in the practice of that worſhip which was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Lord, as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section II.</hi> Concerning Mans incapacity of Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and Serving God acceptably in his natural and unconverted State.</head>
               <p>THat Men in their natural and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted ſtate are uncapable of perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this ſpiritual Worſhip, is certainly true, for that, whilſt they remain in that ſtate, they cannot do any thing that is really good and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30541:8"/>acceptable unto God, being ſubject unto that depraved and ungodly Spirit which leads People into Iniquity, and rules in all the Children of Diſobedience, it comes to paſs, that not only their Words and Deeds, but alſo the Imaginations of their Hearts are evil continually, their Thoughts, Notions and Conceptions concerning Divine and Spiritual matters are unprofitable both to themſelves and others, which thing doth yet further appear from divers Teſtimonies in the Scriptures of Truth. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>That God ſaw the Wickedneſs of man was great in the Earth, and that every Imagination of the thoughts of his Heart was only evil continually, and that it repented the Lord that he had made man on the Earth, and it grieved him at his Heart,</hi> Gen. 6.5, 6. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord looked down from Heaven upon the Children of men, to ſee if there were any that did underſtand and ſeek God,</hi> and ſays, <hi>They are all gone aſide, they are altogether become filthy, there is none that doth good, no not one,</hi> Pſal. 14.2, 3. And again, <hi>But unto the Wicked God ſaith, What haſt thou to do to declare my Statutes, or that thou ſhouldſt take my Covenant into thy Mouth?</hi> Pſal. 50.16. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Heart is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and deſperately wicked, who can know it?</hi> Jer. 17.9. Our Lord ſaith, <hi>An evil man out
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30541:9"/>of the evil treaſure bringeth forth evil things,</hi> Matth. 12.35. Alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of <hi>David,</hi> ſays, <hi>Thero is none Righteous, no not one; there is none that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth; there is none that ſeeketh after God; they are all gone out of the way, they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become unprofitable, there is none that doth good, no not one,</hi> Rom. 3.10, 11, 12. Thus it is to be obſerved, that what is thus ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken relates to men in their natural and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted State, wherein their Souls are dead unto God, and the things of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and cannot live unto him, nor do any ſuch lively act, as to ſerve him, until they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and know the vertue and power of his Grace &amp; Spirit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to quicken them unto God, <hi>That ſo they may ſerve him in the newneſs of the Spirit, and not in the oldneſs of the Letter,</hi> Rom. 7.6.</p>
               <p>For, alas, it is not the bare performance of ſuch things, as are ſuppoſed to be religious duties, that brings into acceptance with God, unleſs the Heart, Soul and Spirit of man be renewed, fitted, prepared and qualified by that which is holy and pure; its the riſe of the performance that God looks at, more then the outward act, he that ſearches, the Heart and tryes the Reins of men, before whom all things are naked and bare, looks
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30541:9"/>not ſo much upon the external Fabrick, as the internal frame of the Soul, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto this man will I look, ſaith the Lord, even to him that is poor, and of a contrite Spirit, and trembleth at my Word,</hi> Iſa. 66.2.</p>
               <p>We read, that although the <hi>Jews</hi> were in the practice of the legal forms of Worſhip, Sacrifice and Oblations, which were by Gods appointment, yet, becauſe their Hearts were defiled, and polluted with Sin and Iniquity, and that they preſented not their Offerings and Sacrifices in a right frame of Spirit, nor under that diſpoſition of Soul that was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; therefore they incurred the wrath and diſpleaſure of God againſt themſelves, and with great aggravation he declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and terribly renounced their Worſhip, as appears in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. and 66.3. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.21, 22, 23. If it was ſo then, that the <hi>Jews</hi> under that Diſpenſation diſpleaſed the Lord in appearing before him, with Offerings and Sacrifices, whilſt their Hearts were polluted and unprepared, as aforeſaid; it may be a caution unto all thoſe that make profeſſion of the pure and undefiled Religion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and of that Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which was inſtituted by him, that they be not found attempting the performance thereof in a ſpiriritual unpreparedneſs, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30541:10"/>whilſt their Hearts and Souls are polluted with Sin and Iniquity, leſt it be ſaid unto them, as it was unto the <hi>Jews, Who hath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this at your Hands to tread my Courts?</hi> Iſa. 1.12.</p>
               <p>Again if the Jewiſh Sacrifices, in the time of the Law, were Sprinkled before they were offered, and the People were Conſecrated that offered them, before they preſented themſelves before the Lord, and that the touching of a dead or nuclear Beaſ then, made People unfit for the Temple or Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, yea, ſociety with the Clean, until they were firſt Sprinkled and Sanctified, as the Scriptures hold out, <hi>Numb.</hi> 8. and chap. 19 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.36. and 30. 16, 17. How car any think ſo meanly of the worſhip, inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt, in Goſpel times, as that it ſhould admit of unprepared and unſanctified Offerings, or allow, that thoſe who are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually defiled with Sin and Iniquity, and in Words or Deeds do daily touch that which is unclean, can in that ſtate well and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably worſhip the pure God, until their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences be ſprinkled from dead works by the blood of Jeſus, and that they be inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prepared and conſecrated, by his divine Spirit and Power, in order to ſerve him.</p>
               <p>It is alſo obſervable, that when the Temple
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30541:10"/>at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was built, before the glory of the Lord deſcended to fill the ſame, it was purified and cleanſed and all polluted ſtuff removed out of it, yea, and the place for the Tabernacle was overlaid with Gold, the moſt pretious clean and pureſt of Mettals, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6, 7, 8, <hi>chapters.</hi> So alſo, before God be truly worſhipped in the inward Temple of the Heart, it muſt alſo be purged of the filth and pollutions that are therein, that ſo it may be fit to receive the Spirit of God, ſo as to be acted by it.</p>
               <p>And yet further, let it be conſidered, how it can be available to the High and Lofty in Mind and Spirit, the Rich and Full in the Pomp and Grandure of the World, the Proud, Covetous and Self-conceited, and ſuch as go on in a road of Unrighteouſneſs, Ungodlineſs and Vanity to utter a multitude of unſeaſoned Words before the Almighty God, or to cry Lord, Lord, whilſt they have neither received, nor are ſubject unto that Bleſſed Spirit which has right to call him ſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. Or how any can rationally ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that he who is clothed with divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Majeſty, who covers himſelf with Light as with a Garment; who ſtretches forth the Heavens like a Curtain, and walks upon the Wings of the Wind; who maketh
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30541:11"/>his Angels Spirits, and his Miniſters a flame of Fire, and is of purer Eyes then to behold Iniquity, can be truly and acceptably Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and Worſhipped by ſuch as do not only reſiſt and rebel againſt that which brings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to acceptance with God, but alſo remain and delight in that which is an abomination unto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section III.</hi> Concerning the neceſſity of receiving the Light, Grace and Spirit of Chriſt in order to quicken and renew to God, and ſo to prepare and qualifie People for his Worſhip and Service.</head>
               <p>SInce then it appears that the Worſhip inſtituted by Chriſt is ſpiritual, and that no man in his natural and unconverted ſtate is capable of performing the ſame accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, we may conclude, and that upon ſure grounds, that the preparation of the holy Spirit is that which is abſolutely neceſſary for men to know in the firſt place, before they go about to perform their Devotions before the Lord: Such as deſire to worſhip God acceptably muſt believe in him whom
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30541:11"/>God hath ſent to redeem loſt man unto him ſelf, viz. the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who by his Light, Grace and Spirit doth manifeſt Sir and Evil in the Hearts and Souls of People and reproveth for the ſame, and alſo lead them that truly own and receive him unto Repentance, and converteth them unto God; he, by his Power revealed in man, doth Crucifie the Fleſh, with the Affections and Luſts; he cleanſes from Sin and Iniquity and quickens the Soul unto God, raiſing up the ſame unto newneſs of Life; ſo that thoſe who in their natural and unconverted ſtate have been Aliens unto God, and Strangers to the Covenant of Promiſe, through Faith in Chriſt, and the work of his Grace and Spirit in their Hearts; ſuch come to be delivered from the Power of Darkneſs, and tranſlated into the Kingdom of Gods dear and wel-beloved Son, to be made Heirs of Glory, Fellow-Citizens with the Saints, of the Houſhold of God, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. and ſo are rendered capable of Worſhipping and Serving God acceptably, according to divine inſtitution, <hi>Being born again</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaid) <hi>not of corruptible Seed, but of incorruptible, by the Word of God which liveth and abideth forever,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.23.</p>
               <p>As to the quickening and renewing Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30541:12"/>of this divine Spirit and Light of Chriſt, the Saints and Children of God have not only a living and bleſſed Experience thereof in this our day, but alſo the Scriptures do afford us divers Teſtimonies concerning the ſame; <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſaith, <hi>As the Father raiſeth up the Dead, and quickeneth them, even ſo the Son quickeneth whom he will,</hi> John 5.21. Again, <hi>It is the Spirit that quickeneth, the Fleſh profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing,</hi> John 6.63. And alſo the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> ſaith, <hi>If any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his; and if Chriſt he in you, the Body is Dead becauſe of Sin, but the Spirit is Life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Righteouſneſs; but if the Spirit of him that raiſed up Jeſus from the Dead dwell in you, he that raiſed up Chriſt from the Dead ſhall alſo quicken your mortal Bodies, by his Spirit that dwelleth in you; therefore Brethren we are Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors not to the Fleſh, to live after the Fleſh; for if ye live after the Fleſh ye ſhall Dye, but if ye through the Spirit do mortifie the deeds of the Body ye ſhall Live; for as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God,</hi> Rom. 8.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. And again the ſame Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> ſays, <hi>And you hath he quickened who were dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins; yea, God who is rich in Mercy, for his great Love wherewith he loved
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30541:12"/>us, even when we were dead in Sins, hath quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us together with Chriſt, (by Grace are ye ſaved) and hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit together in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Epheſ. 2.1, 4, 5, 6. From whence it is very clear and plain, that it is the Spirit of Chriſt that quickeneth the Souls of thoſe who have been dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins, and that if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt he is none of his, and if he be none of Chriſts, he is none of the true Church, and conſequently no true Worſhipper; Again he ſays, <hi>That as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God;</hi> and if Sons then Heirs and Members of the true Church, who worſhip God in the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Moreover, as the Lord Jeſus Chriſt by his divine Spirit and Power doth thus work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hearts and Souls of thoſe that receive him, in order to cleanſe from Sin and Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to raiſe up into newneſs of Life; ſo alſo it is he only, by his holy Light and Spirit, that truly prepared and diſpoſes the Hearts of People for the ſervice of God, and opens the Myſteries of Truth unto the Sons and Daughters of Men: <hi>He it is that hath the Key of</hi> David, <hi>that opens, and no man ſhutteth, and ſhutteth, and no man openeth,</hi> Rev. 3.9. And without him the viſion of divine things are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30541:13"/>as a Book that is Sealed, and hid from the wiſdom of man in the Fall, and no man is worthy to open the Seals thereof; for which cauſe, it ſeems, <hi>John</hi> Wept, as we read in the Revelation, <hi>And I ſaw, in the right hand of him that ſat on the Throne, a Book written within, and on the back-ſide ſealed with ſeven Seals; and I ſaw a ſtrong Angel proclaiming with a loud voice, Who is worthy to open the Book and to looſe the Seales thereof? and no man in Heaven, nor in Earth, neither under the Earth was able to open the Book, neither to look thereon; and I wept much, becauſe none was found worthy to open the Book, neither to look thereon; and one of the Elders ſaid unto me, Weep not; behold the Lion of the Tribe of</hi> Judah, <hi>the Root of</hi> David, <hi>hath prevailed to open the Book, and to looſe the ſeven Seals thereof,</hi> Rev. 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. By the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Juda,</hi> is to be underſtood the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who prevailed with the Father to open the Book of Truth, and to looſe the Seals thereof; without whom no man is able to open the ſame, be he never ſo Wiſe in worldly Wiſdom, and never ſo Learned in natural Arts and Sciences, as may hereafter, in its due and proper place, more fully and at large appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:30541:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Section IV.</hi> Concerning the Goſpel Church and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Temple.</head>
               <p>AS it is the Light, Spirit and Power of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt that truely quickens, and renews People unto God, and renders them capable of performing that Spiritual Worſhip, which is acceptable unto him; ſo alſo it is by the vertue and influence of the ſame Spirit and Power that the Lords Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have been, and are ſtated in a joynt Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and Communion, and are drawn into an outward and viſible Society, and ſo come under the name of a Church; yet for a better underſtanding of the word Church, or what is meant thereby, it may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in a two fold reſpect, <hi>Firſt,</hi> As it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all whatſoever, of every Nation, Kindred, Tongue and People, whom the Lord God by his univerſal Spirit and Power (revealed and made manifeſt in and through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt) doth truly call and gather out of the Life and Spirit of the World, and the Pollutions and Defilements thereof, into that Pure, Holy and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30541:14"/>State of Faith and Life, wherein they are cccepted of God, and owned by him as his Children and People, which make up that one, true, Univerſal, or Catholic Church, out of which (indeed) there is no Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The word Chuch may be taken for a certain number of Perſons who (being Members of this Univerſal Church) are gathered into an outward and viſible So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and do Meet and Aſſemble themſelves together, really to wait upon, and Worſhip the Living God, and to bear a Teſtimony for the Truth againſt Error. The Church, in the firſt ſence, in Scripture terms, is called, <hi>The New, Holy and Heavenly</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſembly and Church of the Firſt-Born, the Lambs Bride,</hi> and <hi>the City of the Living God,</hi> Heb. 12.22, 23. Rev. 19.7. and 21.2, 9, 10. The Church in the latter ſence we have it often mentioned in the Scriptures, as appears <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.2. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. John <hi>writteth to the ſeven Churches in</hi> Aſia. Thus it is not the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Houſe, Frabrick or Building of Wood or Stone, that is or can be truly term'd the Church, or Houſe of God, in this Goſpel day, as ſome vainly do conceive, (and therefore do aſcribe ſome imaginary Sanctity or Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereunto) but it is the Aſſembly of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30541:14"/>Believers, in this ſence gather'd together as aforeſaid, who are the Evangelical Temple, Goſpel Church, and Houſe of God, the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments whereof are not the Embroideries and Furnitures of wordly Art and Wealth, but the Gifts and Graces of the holy Spirit, Love, Meekneſs, Faith, Patience, Long-ſuffering, Humility, Self-denial and Charity, with other Chriſtian Vertues.</p>
               <p>'Tis true the <hi>Jews</hi> under the old Covenant and Diſpenſation of the Law had an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Temple, where they were to Worſhip, as in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 9. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7. and becauſe the Lord was pleaſed to Hollow it for his Name, and honour it with his Preſence; as alſo to cauſe an outward Glory and Majeſty to appear there, by cauſing Fire from Heaven to conſume their Sacrifices, &amp;c. therefore it was called the Houſe of God, as is manifeſt in the writings of the old Teſtament. And alſo the Lord Jeſus, before he was offered up, gives it that Name, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.16. But then, after Chriſt was offered up, and the pure ſpiritual Worſhip and Service came to be Exalted, and born Teſtimony unto, by the Apoſtles and Servants of Chriſt, that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Temple being left deſolate of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Preſence of God, it came to Ruin, according to the ſaying of the Lord Jeſus,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30541:15"/>and the true Miniſters of the Goſpel plainly teſtified, <hi>That the moſt high dwelt not in Tein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples made with Hands,</hi> Acts 7.48. and 17.24, 25. <hi>Neither was he Worſhipped with mens hands, as though he needed any thing, ſeeing he giveth to all Life and Breath, and all things; but he is Worſhipped in Spirit,</hi> John 4.24. <hi>His Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is with men, he will dwell with them, and they ſhall be his People,</hi> Rev. 21.3. Therefore the Apoſtle thus writes to the Church at <hi>Corinth, Know ye not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you; if any man deſile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy; for the Temple of God is holy, which Temple ye are,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.16, 17. Again, <hi>Ye are the Temple of the Living God, as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk in them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People,</hi> 2 Cor 6.16. And alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, <hi>Ye alſo as lively Stones are built up a ſpiritual Houſe, an holy Prieſthood to offer up ſpiritual Sacrifices acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.5. Again the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> expreſſeth himſelf thus, Moſes <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily was faithful in all his Houſe, as a Servant, for a Teſtimony of thoſe things which were to be ſpoken after; but Chriſt as a Son, ever his own Houſe, whoſe Houſe we are, if we hold faſt the Confidence, and the rejoycing of the Hope from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30541:15"/>unto the end,</hi> Heb. 3.5, 6. By all which Teſtimonies its plainly manifeſt, that the Saints and Children of God are that Spiritual Houſe, and Evangelical Temple, wherein the Glory and preſence of God is ſpiritually known and witneſſed in this Goſpel day, which is yet further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and held forth in that remarkable paſſage of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the Church at <hi>Epheſus, Now therefore ye are no more Strangers and Forreigners, but fellow Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens with the Saints; and of the houſhold of God, and are built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief Corner Stone, in whom all the Building fitly framed together groweth unto an holy Temple in the Lord, in whom you alſo are builded together for an Habitation of God through the Spirit,</hi> Epheſ. 2.19, 20, 21, 22.</p>
               <p>Howbeit Chriſtians have Meeting-Places, tho not in Jewiſh or Heathen Pomp and State, but plain and ſuitable for that purpoſe, anſwerable to the ſimplicity of the Life and Doctrine of their bleſſed Lord, who teaches Humility, Plainneſs and Moderation upon all accounts; it is not ſimply the Place, but the Perſons there aſſembled that he has a regard unto, who meet in his Name and Fear, ſuch doth he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30541:16"/>honour with his bleſſed Preſence whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are met together to wait upon him, and by the vertue of his Grace and Spirit he doth ſtrengthen and confirm his Children and People, enabling them to perform that Worſhip and Service which is acceptable unto God in this Goſpel day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section V.</hi> Concerning ſilent waiting upon God, for the help and concurrence of his holy Spirit, in the performance of Divine Worſhip.</head>
               <p>INaſmuch as thoſe who have received the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his bleſſed Name and Truth, are ſo drawn into an outward and viſible Society, as that they do Meet and Aſſemble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together at ſeaſonable and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient times and places, according to the practice of the true Believers in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times; ſo when they are aſſembled, it ought to be the care of all to abſtain from their own Actings, Thoughts and Imaginations, and to be inwardly retir'd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30541:16"/>in their Minds in a holy watchfulneſs and dependency upon the Lord, that ſo being gathered together in his Name, they may be ſenſible of his bleſſed Preſence amongſt them, according to his promiſe, <hi>Where two or three</hi> (ſays he) <hi>are gathered together in my Name, there will I be in the midſt of them.</hi> This Name is not only an outward and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral Name, but a pretious, living &amp; power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Name, wherein true Comfort, Strength &amp; Safety is nor is it an outward gathering only, but an inward gathering in Heart, Mind and Spirit unto that which is pure and holy; therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>I beſeech you Brithren by the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and by our gathering together unto him,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.1. By which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that the Saints gathering was unto Chriſt, his Spirit and Power, and as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one are thus gathered in Spirit, as well as outwardly in Perſon, the ſecret Power and Vertue of the divine Spirit is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently known to Revive and Refreſh their Souls, and the pure Motions and Breathings thereof are witneſſed; from which as Words of Declaration, Prayers or Praiſes to God do ariſe, the pure, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and acceptable Worſhip and Service of God is known, yea tho there be not a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30541:17"/>word ſpoken, yet in poſſible that the true Spiritual Worſhip may be performed and the Church of Chriſt Edified.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, although this inward Silence, and ſpiritual waiting upon God be a very great &amp; neceſſary Duty, and in order pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds all real acts of Divine Worſhip; foraſmuch as it is an inward retirement of the Mind from all its own Motions, Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Imaginations and vain Speculations, and a meer dependance upon God for the help and influence of his Grace and Spirit, yet it is very ſtrange and oppoſit to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Will and Wiſdom of Man, whoſe roving Imaginations and running worldly Deſires, Vauities and Delights are not eaſily ſubjected and brought to ſilence, and ſuch are ready to think all time loſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is not ſomething ſpoken that's obvious to the outward Senſes, not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that ſo long as the natural Spirit of man is the firſt and chief Author and Actor of him in his Devotions towards God, ſo as that he does not firſt wait for a Divine Guide to direct him he cannot worſhip ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably, nor bring forth any thing of himſelf but the Fruit of the faln, natural and corrupt Root; and indeed this is one great reaſon why many ſober and diſcreet
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30541:17"/>Perſons, in this our Age, cannot joyn with the ſeveral forms of Worſhip now extant in the World, but under a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encious Exerciſe and Concern do diſſent from them, not in any ſtubbornneſs (as ſome would charge them) but really for Conſcience ſake, leſt they ſhould offend God in joyning with that which he by his Spirit hath made them ſenſible of that he takes no delight in; for what is a heap of the moſt Pathetical Words that can be uttered unto God Almighty, when they are both begun, carried on and concluded in mans own natural Will and Strengh, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the motion or influence of the Spirit of God, which is and muſt needs be of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity for enabling People to perform that Spiritual Worſhip which was inſtituted by our Lord, and is now practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by his People.</p>
               <p>Yet nevertheleſs, although this inward retiredneſs and ſpiritual waiting upon God be almoſt a myſtery to the World, and very hard &amp; difficult unto men in their natural &amp; unregenerate Sate, yet it is that whereby the ſpiritual man renews his ſtrength in the Lord, &amp; it is frequently commanded &amp; born teſtimonyunto in the holy Scriptures, as appears by the following Texts, which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30541:18"/>the Reader may peruſe at his Leaſure, <hi>Job</hi> 14.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.1 <hi>and</hi> 62 5. <hi>and</hi> 69.3. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.25, 26. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.42. <hi>and</hi> 25.13. <hi>and</hi> 26.41. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.37. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. See alſo, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.4. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.15, 16. <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Job.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p>Moreover this ſilence or ſilent waiting for a ſeaſon, before Words be ſpoken re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the Worſhip and Service of God, doth not thus only appear to be agreeable to Scripture Teſtimony, but alſo is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable even to Reaſon &amp; natural Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in other things, for he that would learn of a Maſter any Art or Science, ought not to fall on ſpeaking or acting immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately of his own Mind and Will, &amp; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue unquiet, but rather ſhould be ſilent, for a ſeaſon, to hear his Maſter inſtruct him what and how he ſhall door ſay, and then proceed. So alſo he that undertakes to ſerve a Maſter ſhould not run haſtily on to do things in his own Time and Will, nor yet to deaffen his Maſter with Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, though it were in Praiſes of him; but he ought rather to wait to hear his Maſter ſpeak, and inform him what and how to do, and then proceed to act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Directions. Even ſo thoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30541:18"/>that deſire to be taught of God and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by him in Righteouſneſs, ought not to keep themſelves continually buſied with their own Imaginations and Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but patiently to wait upon God, that ſo he by his Grace and Spirit may Teach and Inſtruct them; and alſo thoſe that deſire to ſerve God (in this Goſpel day) ought not to run haſtily about the ſame, in their own corrupt, forward and unrenewed. Wills and Minds, but dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to attend upon God to feel the Strength and Counſel of his Spirit in ſuch undertakings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section VI.</hi> Concerning the Preparation, Call and Ordination of Goſpel Miniſters.</head>
               <p>AS it is the duty of every Chriſtian to wait upon God for the help and ſtrength of his holy Spirit, in order to ſit, prepare &amp; qualifie them for the Worſhip &amp; Service of God; ſo it is by the Power and Vertue of the Divine Spirit that every true Evangeliſt and Goſpel Miniſter is ordained, prepared and ſupplied in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30541:19"/>work of the Miniſtry, otherwiſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be truly ſaid to be a Minſter of the Spirit; for as none could be Miniſters of the Letter who had thence no ground of their Call, nor directions therefrom, how, when, nor after what manner they ſhould Miniſter; neither can any be reall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Spirit, who are not called, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, fitted and prepared by it, nor are acquainted with the motions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections thereof, in order to draw, move, act, influence, aſſiſt and go before them in the Work and Service of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>As for the Service of the <hi>Jews,</hi> under the Diſpenſation of the Law, there was a certain Tribe allotted for the Miniſtry, which was the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> ſo that then People needed not to queſtion who ſhould be Prieſts and Miniſters of holy things, for that the Lord God by his Servant <hi>Moſes</hi> did ſet apart divers of the aforeſaid Tribe for the Prieſtood, and other Offices; as alſo he did direct how, and after what manner their Worſhip and Service was to be performed, as may be ſeen at large in the writings of <hi>Moſes</hi>— And beſides that it pleaſed God at divers times under that Diſpenſation, by the immediate Teſtimony of his holy Spirit, to raiſe up
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30541:19"/>ſeveral Perſons to Teach, Inſtruct and Reprove the People, as <hi>Samuel, Nathan, Elias, Eliſha, Jeremiah, Amos,</hi> and others of the Prophets; but now under the new Covenant, and Diſpenſation of the Goſpel, there is no ſuch Tribe of People allotted, &amp; ſet a part particularly for the Miniſtry, as was under the Law, neither is the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Celebrated after the manner of the <hi>Jews</hi> in divers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, nor is it attended with thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ceremonies, and ſhadowing Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, as was that of the <hi>Jews;</hi> for the Chriſtian Worſhip &amp; Service is performed in Spirit &amp; in Truth, (as hath been before and ſtill yet may be further obſerved) and therein it greatly Excelleth, and far Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended that under the Law, being under the adminiſtration of Life and Glory, wherein the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is alone ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted as high Prieſt and Prophet of his People, who being the Lord of true Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, doth ſpiritually Call, Ordain, Conſtitute and Qualifie the Miniſters of the new Teſtament, and Inſtruct them in the Spiritual Law, which is the delight of Gods People.</p>
               <p>That the Apoſtles and Servants of Chriſt, in the Primitive times, were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30541:20"/>and qualified by the Divine Spirit to, and for, the Work of the Miniſtry, is ſo plain and clear that none need queſtion it, unleſs it be ſuch who at this day would aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and arrogate unto themſelves the name and title of Goſpel Miniſters, by Virtue of ſome outward Ordination, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the call, help and influence of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit; unto ſuch I ſay it greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves them to conſider how, and when, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt did transfer that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer unto man which is only peculiar un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf; I know that thoſe who deſpiſe the motion and diclares of the Grace of God in themſelves, and yet would be eſteemed Miniſters, are apt to deny, that the Power and Influence of the holy Spirit is of abſolute neceſſity for the Call and Qualification of a Goſpel Miniſter, and therefore do wholly betake themſelves to an outward Ordination for a refuge, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſuch would have nothing to ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in that reſpect, for what they pretend to. 'Tis certain, and always granted, that thoſe whom God is pleaſed to Call and Qualifie by his Grace and Spirit to and for the Work and Service of the Goſpel, are to be owned and approved of by his Church and People; but then it does not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30541:20"/>therefore follow that any who have only attained unto ſome degree of humane Learning &amp; Knowledg in Arts &amp; Sciences, can be thereby fitted for the Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, or that ſuch Perſon, under thoſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, can be rightly qualified for that Work &amp; Service by the Power of man, without the call, help, influence and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the bleſſed and holy Spirit and Power of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, wherein the true power of Ordination ſtands, and not in men, as men, but in the Spirit of Chriſt, which ought to have the ſupream Government in the hearts of men, and thoſe who are truly called, ordained and qualified by the divine Spirit for the Work and Service of the Goſpel, are accepted of God and approved of by his Church and People, as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>He that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God, and approved of Men,</hi> Rom. 14.18. Alſo we read that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> when he took his leave of the Elders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he thus expreſſed himſelf, <hi>Take heed therefore unto your ſelves and to all the Flock, over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you Overſeers, to feed the Church of God which he hath purchaſed with his own Blood,</hi> Acts 20.28. And again the holy
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30541:21"/>Ghoſt ſaid unto the Prophets &amp; Teachers which were in the Church at <hi>Antioch, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate me</hi> Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Saul, <hi>for the Work whereunto I have called them; and when they had Faſted and Prayed, and laid their hands on them, they ſent them away; ſo</hi> (its ſaid) <hi>they being ſent forth by the holy Ghoſt depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto</hi> Soleucia, <hi>and from thence they ſailed to</hi> Cyprus, <hi>and when they were at</hi> Salamis <hi>they Preached the Word of God in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues of the</hi> Jews, Acts 13.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. From whence its obſervable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Elders of the Church at <hi>Epheſus</hi> were made Overſeers there, by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That it was the Holy Ghoſt that called <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> unto the Work and Service of the Goſpel, and that it was the Holy Ghoſt that ſent them.</p>
               <p>By which it appears, that the power of Calling, and Ordaining Goſpel Miniſters, reſides in the Holy Spirit, and that thoſe who are Called and Ordained thereby, are approved by the Church, being ſet apart by God for the Service they are called un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, which thing doth very well agree with the ſaying of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the Church at <hi>Corinth, God hath ſet ſome in the Church, firſt Apoſtles, ſecondarily Prophets,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30541:21"/>Teachers, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 12.28. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> he faith, <hi>When he aſcended up on high, he led Captivity Captive, and gave gifts unto Men; and he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, &amp; ſome Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and ſome Paſtours and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 4.8, 11, 12. By which it alſo appears that it was not Man but God that ſet Apoſtles, Prophets and Teachers in the Church, and that it was through the gift of God that they were made Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtours and Teachers, and thereby were they rendered capable of perfecting the Saints, of the work of the Miniſtry, and of edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Furthermore it is obſervable that when the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was giving an account before King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> how the Lord met with him in his way to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> he ſays, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> told him, <hi>For that purpoſe he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto him, to make him a Miniſter and a Witneſs both of thoſe things which he had ſeen, and of thoſe things he would appear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in,</hi> Acts 26.16. And alſo the ſame Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians</hi> ſays, <hi>When it pleaſed God (who ſeper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d me from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30541:22"/>my Mothers Womb, and called me by his Grace) to reveal his Son in me, that I might preach him among the Heathen, immediatly I confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not with Fleſh and Blood, neither went I up to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to them that were Apoſtles before me, but I went into</hi> Arabia, <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned again unto</hi> Damaſcus, Gal. 1.15, 16, 17. And again, in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> he ſays, <hi>I thank Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, who hath enabled me, for that he counted me faithful putting me into the Miniſtry,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.12. All which doth yet further ſet forth, that it was the Lord Jeſus Chriſt that made <hi>Paul</hi> a Miniſter, and that it was by his Grace, Spirit and Power that he was enabled and put into the Miniſtry; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does it appear that he went up to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> at that time to be ordain'd by them who were Apoſtles before him, but he went into <hi>Arabia</hi> and returned again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> as is before ſet forth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Objection,</hi> Its probable ſome may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and ſay, <hi>That though the Apoſtles, and Miniſters of Christ, in the primitive times were immediately called to that Work and Service by the Spirit of God, yet it was for an extraordinary Work, and if any now do pretend to an immediate call, they ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it by Miracles.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:30541:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Unto which I Anſwer, That although it was an extraordinary Work which they were ſent to do, yet the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree does not change the kind; <hi>They were to preach Chriſt Crucified and riſen again, and were to preach Repentance and remiſſion of Sins through his Name: They were to turn People from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God, that ſo they might receive forgiveneſs of Sins, and an Inheritance among them which were Sanctified by Faith in Chriſt,</hi> Acts 26.18. Even ſo are the Miniſters of Chriſt in this our day to hold out the ſame Doctrine, according to the Diſpenſation of the Goſpel committed unto them; nor is there any neceſſity for Miracles to be wrought by thoſe who are called of God, in this our day, to the Work of the Miniſtry for the confirmation of their Teſtimony, when as they preach no new Goſpel, but what was preacht by the Servants of Chriſt in the primitive times, and is already confirmed by the Miracles of Chriſt, and of his Apoſtles; and when nothing is offered but what is anſwerable to Truth, and agreeable to the Teſtimony of the Scriptures; and beſides that, we do not find that either <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, or ſeveral others of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30541:23"/>did any Miracles, and yet they were both Immediatly &amp; Extraordinarily ſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section VII.</hi> Concerning Women Preaching.</head>
               <p>AS this Divine Spirit hath been, and is extended univerſally unto all People, at certain times and ſeaſons, during the day of their Viſitation, according to the Good-will and Pleaſure of our God, and that in order to call, gather and renew them unto himſelf; ſo it hath been the good Pleaſure of our God to call and qualifie whom he thinks convenient for the Work and Service of the Goſpel; and upon this account it may pleaſe him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to make uſe of Women as well as Men, according to his Promiſe by the Prophet <hi>Joel, And it ſhall come to paſs after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that I will pour out my Spirit upon all Fleſh, and your Sons and your Daughters ſhall Propheſie, your old Men ſhall dream Dreams, your young Men ſhall ſee Viſions; and alſo upon the Servants, and upon the Hand Maids in thoſe dayes will I pour out my Spirit.</hi> This Propheſie had a reſpect to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30541:23"/>the Goſpel Day, and related to the more plentiful effuſion of the Holy Spirit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Diſpenſation, both upon Male and Female, as was witneſſed at the day of <hi>Penticoſt; When the Apoſtles with the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and</hi> Mary <hi>the Mother of</hi> Jeſus, <hi>with his Brethren, were gathered together,</hi> its ſaid, <hi>They were all filled with the Holy Ghoſt, and began to ſpeak with other Tongues, as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit gave them utterance,</hi> Acts 1.13, 14. and 2.4. And if All were filled with the Holy Ghoſt, and Spoke, then Women as well as Men, foraſmuch as Women were there preſent with the Men, as the Text holds out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Now ſo it is that many are enclined to object againſt Women Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Preaching, and upon that account do alledge the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34, 35. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In anſwer whereunto I ſay, that although theſe Texts may be myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally underſtood, as ſome have obſerved, yet if we take them literally, and withal conſider the ſcope and tendency of the Apoſtles Words, both before and after, and compare other Expreſſions of his with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30541:24"/>thoſe, (which will be one way to give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction concerning his meaning) and alſo obſerve the Practice of the Church upon thoſe accounts, it will appear that Women, as Women, or of that Sex, and for no other reaſon, are not prohibited to Preach.</p>
               <p>Its obſervable, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in that Chapter, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. was not treating who, or what Sex ſhould Propheſie, &amp; what not; but he was ſpeaking of that order and decency which ſuch as Propheſie ought to obſerve; he was treating of Spiritual Gifts, and of Speaking and Praying in an unknown Tongue, and of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod that ſuch ſhould uſe; <hi>If any Man</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſpeak in an unknown Tongue, let it be by two, or at the moſt by three, and that by courſe, and let one interpret; but if there be no Interpreter let him keep ſilence in the Church, and let him ſpeak to himſelf, and to God; let the Prophets ſpeak two or three, and let the other judge; and if any thing be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to him that ſitteth by, let the firſt hold his peace; for ye may all Propheſie one by one,</hi> &amp;c. then he adds, <hi>Let your Women keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in the Churches; for it is not permitted unto them to ſpeak, but they are commanded to be under obedience, as alſo ſaith the Law, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30541:24"/>if they will learn any thing let them ask their Husbands at home, for it is a ſhame for a Woman to ſpeak in the Church.</hi> And ſo he goes on, and concludes that Chapter with theſe Words, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By all which it is very clear &amp; plain, that the Apoſtles drift was to adviſe them unto a decent, comely and orderly method in the Church, and that he did not intend a general prohibition unto Women, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they were called or qualified, for then had he not only oppoſed their appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Practice in the Church, but even his own Teſtimony in the very ſame Epiſtle, where he ſaith, <hi>Every Woman that Prayeth or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſieth, with her Head uncovered, diſhonoureth her Head,</hi> chap. 11.5. Thus he is ſo far from diſallowing of Women Praying or Propheſing, that he adviſeth how they ſhall be covered, and demean themſelves in the performance of ſuch Services and Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Again the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Ye may all Propheſie one by one,</hi> and if All, then Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as well as Men, foraſmuch as without any reſtriction he directs his Epiſtle to the Church of God at <hi>Corinth,</hi> which no queſtion conſiſted of Women as well as Men; if then theſe words <hi>[Ye may all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30541:25"/>Propheſie]</hi> have relation unto them to whom the Apoſtle directed that Epiſtle, as is certain; then Women may Propheſie as well as Men, provided they be truly called and qualified by the Spirit of God, and that any thing be revealed and enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them to declare and hold forth unto People from him, who is and ought to be the ſole orderer and diſpoſer of the Hearts and Spirits of all his People</p>
               <p>And as for that ſaying of his unto <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> it is much to the ſame purpoſe, for he was ſpeaking how Women ſhould adorn themſelves, and how they ſhould not adorn themſelves, then he ſubjoyns, <hi>Let the Woman learn in ſilence with all ſubjection, but I ſuffer not a Woman to Teach, nor to uſurp Authority over the Man, but to be Silent,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.9, 10, 11, 12. There is no queſtion but there were ſuch Women at <hi>Epheſus</hi> (where <hi>Timothy</hi> then was) who had need of this care to be taken concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and at <hi>Corinth</hi> too, ſuch as were unlearned, proud and tattling Women, not come to the true ſilence; and therefore he ſays, <hi>Let the Women learn in ſilence with all ſubjection.</hi> Again its probable there might be ſuch as would be teaching and uſurping authority over the Man, ſuch had
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30541:25"/>need to be ſilent indeed, (that's without diſpute) for if they were for uſurping authority over the man, they were very unfit to be Teachers of others.</p>
               <p>But what of all this, although Proud, Vain, Tattling, Ignorant and Unlearned Women are not to be permitted to Speak in the Church, nor to make diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance there, with their unſeaſonable and unlearned Queſtions and Diſcourſes; but are to learn in Silence with all Subjection, and to be under Obedience, as alſo ſaith the Law; yet it does not therefore: follow but that ſuch Women as are become Meek, Humble, Sober, Grave, Temperate, Wiſe and Diſcreet, and keep their Place and Station in the bleſſed Truth, and have been content to learn in ſilence with all ſubjection, may do and perform ſuch Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and Devotions, in the Church of Chriſt, as they may be called unto, and have a neceſſity from the Lord laid upon them to be found in the practice of, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in publick Declarations and Teſtimonies for God and his Truth, or in Prayers, Praiſes and Thankſgivings unto him.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures do afford us divers Teſtimonies that Women as well as Men
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30541:26"/>have been concerned upon theſe accompts, to paſs by divers that might be mentioned, whoſe Names are recorded in the writings of the Old Teſtament, in whom the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord has been ſo prevalent, that they have appeared Zealous for the God of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> we ſhall only ſpeak of thoſe mention'd in the writings of the New Teſtament, who have been concerned in the Work and Service of the Goſpel: We Read that <hi>Anna</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Phanuel</hi> was a Propheteſs, and Preached to the People in the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the Clorious Day of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Redemption, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.36, 37, 38. The next is the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Samaria,</hi> with whom Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Converſed, ſhe was taught of Chriſt himſelf that he was the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and then ſhe went and Publiſh't the ſame in the City <hi>Sychar, John</hi> 4.26.28, 29. Again, we find that ridings of Chriſts Reſurrection was firſt publiſh't by a Woman, viz. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and that ſhe was commanded by Chriſt himſelf to go to his Brethren and ſay unto them, <hi>I aſcend unto my Father and your Father, and to my God and your God,</hi> John 20.17, 18. And alſo <hi>Philip</hi> the Evangeliſt, who was one of the ſeven mentioned <hi>Acts</hi> 6.5. had four Daughters
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30541:26"/>Virgins, which did Propheſie, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.8, 9. Moreover the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf was ſo far from diſcouraging Women upon theſe accounts, that he mentions ſeveral being concerned with him in the Work and Service of Goſpel, he begins the 16 chapter to the <hi>Romnus</hi> thus, <hi>I commend unto you</hi> Phebe <hi>our Siſter, which is a Servant of the Church which is at</hi> Cenchrea. Again, <hi>Greet</hi> Priſcilla <hi>and</hi> Aquila <hi>my fellow helpers in Chriſt Jeſus. Salute</hi> Tryphena <hi>and</hi> Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſa <hi>who labour in the Lord. Salute the beloved</hi> Perſis, <hi>which laboured much in the Lord,</hi> Rom. 16.3, 12. All theſe were Women except <hi>Aquila.</hi> Alſo the ſame Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians</hi> writeth thus, <hi>And I intreat thee alſo true Yoke-Fellow, help thoſe Women that laboured with me in the Goſpel, with</hi> Clement <hi>alſo, and other my fellow Labourers, whoſe Names are written in the Book of Life,</hi> Phil. 4.3.</p>
               <p>Thus it is manifeſt that ſerious, godly and wel-diſpoſed Women, whom the Lord by his Grace and Spirit ſtired up in former Ages to ſerve him, and to bear a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for his Name and Truth, were owned by the Apoſtle in their Service, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of in the Church of Chriſt, and indeed they ought to be ſo ſtill; wherein it is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30541:27"/>manifeſt, that their Exerciſe and Service ſtands in the Truth, and in the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of that Divine Spirit and Power <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is neither Jew nor Greek, Bond nor Free, Male nor Female, but all are one even in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Gal. 3 28. who by the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his free Spirit may exerciſe whom he pleaſes in Building up, Strengthening and Confirming his Church and People, as alſo in bearing a Teſtimony unto his Bleſſed and Holy Name amongſt the Sons and Daughters of Men.</p>
               <p>And yet nevertheleſs, as it hath been ſo it is, and ought to be obſerv'd, that ſuch Women as are not truly called &amp; qualified for ſuch Services in the Church, ought not to preſume to Speak and Teach there, but to learn in Silence with all due Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and indeed it concerns all, both Men and Women, to be very careful in theſe reſpects, and alſo to be cautious that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of divine motion they be not found going into fooliſh Whimſies and Extreams, out of the Liberties and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of Chriſtian Prudence, Decency and Moderation; but that all keep under the Guidance, Conduct, Government, Order and Diſcipline of the bleſſed and holy Spirit and Power of our Lord and Saviour
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30541:27"/>Jeſus Chriſt; otherwiſe it may be ſaid of Men as well as Women, <hi>Let them keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in the Church, for it is not permitted unto them to Speak in a ſpiritual unprepared<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in diſ-union with God and his People, nor in any rule, undecent or diſorderly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; For our God is not the author of Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but of Peace, as in all the Churches of the Saints,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.33.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section VIII.</hi> Concerning the Riſe of Goſpel Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, and the Qualifications of Goſpel Miniſters, ſhowing that they are not from Human Learning, Worldly Wiſdom and Natural Arts and Sciences, but from the Divine Spirit.</head>
               <p>FRom what hath been ſaid concerning the Chriſtian Miniſtry it is clearly manifeſt, that the Vertue and Power of the Divine Spirit is abſolutely neceſſary for the Qualifying, Calling and Conſtituting of a Goſpel Miniſter, and that it is by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30541:28"/>help, motion and aſſiſtance thereof, that every true Evangeliſt and Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is to be acted and ſupplied in the performance of their Duties and Services, otherwiſe it does no way appear that they can either be acceptable unto God, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial unto men, inaſmuch as man of himſelf, in his natural and unrenewed State (notwithſtanding his outward abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, as to Human Learning) is (as it were) a Stranger unto God, and really anacquainted with the Myſteries of his Heavenly Kingdom; for although School Learning, Worldly Wiſdom and Human Arts and Sciences, are much look't upon and applauded, in this our Age, as Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications abſolutely neceſſary for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Miniſtry; yet we no where find any ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſs laid upon the ſame in the Scriptures, but on the contrary it rather appears from thence, that the knowledge of Divine and Spiritual Myſteries are hid from the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſe, and is revealed unto thoſe who by the vertue of the holy Spirit are born again, and ſo are become Babes in Chriſt: Unto this our Lord Jeſus has given a very plain and ample Teſtimony, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21, 22. <hi>In that hour Jeſus rejoyced in Spirit and ſaid, I thank thee O Father, Lord of Heaven
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30541:28"/>and Earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent, and haſt revealed them unto Babes; even ſo Father, for it ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good in thy ſight: All things are delivered to me of my Father, and no mar knoweth who the Son is but the Father, and who the Father is but the Son, and he to whom the Son will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, its obſervable, that although the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was learned ſufficiently, and brought up at <hi>Gamaliel</hi>'s Feet, yet all his Learning and Knowledge could not truly open his Underſtanding in Divine and Spriritual Matters, for whilſt he was acted by that Wiſdom which was from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low he was ſo blind that he ran on in a fierce career to Perſecute the People of God,<note place="margin">Acts 11.29.</note> and was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Mad againſt them; yea, he confeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf, that he was <hi>a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>a Perſecutor and injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> and ſays, <hi>That beyond meaſure he Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Church of God and waſted it:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.13.</note> But after it pleaſed God to meet with him, to call him by his Grace, and to reveal his Son in him, he came to learn an other Leſſon, he was ſo far from applauding and exalting worldly Wiſdom, and human Arts and Sciences as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30541:29"/>Qualifications of abſolute neceſſity for a Goſpel Miniſter, that he rather ſeems to oppoſe the ſame, ſaying, <hi>Where is the Wiſe? Where is the Scribe? Where is the Diſputer of this World? Hath not God made Fooliſh the Wiſdom of this World? For after that in the wiſdom of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20, 21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the World by wiſdom knew not God, it pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſs of Preaching to ſave them that Believe: For the</hi> Jews <hi>require a Sign, and the</hi> Greeks <hi>ſeek after Wiſdom; but we preach Chriſt Crucified, unto the</hi> Jews <hi>a Stumbling-block, and unto the</hi> Greeks <hi>Fooliſhneſs; but unto them which are called, both</hi> Jews <hi>and</hi> Greeks, <hi>Chriſt the Power of God, and the Wiſdom of God.</hi> And alſo he ſays, verſe the 27th, <hi>But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the World to confound the wiſe, and God hath choſen the weak things of the World to confound the things that are mighty, and baſe things of the World, and things that are diſpiſed, hath God choſen; yea, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are, that no Fleſh ſhould glory in his Preſence.</hi> Thus we ſee the Apoſtle doth much endeavour to debaſe the Wiſdom of the World, and to exalt the Power and Wiſdom of God, as yet ſtill further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the following Chapter, where he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30541:29"/>begins to ſpeak concerning himſelf, and his manner of coming unto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>And I Brethren, when I came to you, came not with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Speech or of Wiſdom, declaring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the Teſtimony of God, for I determined not to know any thing among you, ſave Jeſus Chriſt, and him Crucified, and I was with you in Weakneſs, and in Fear, and in much Trembling, and my Speech, and my Preaching was not with enticing Words of Mans Wiſdom, but in the demonſtration of the Spirit, and of Power; that your Faith might not ſtand in the Wiſdom of Men, but in the Power of God.</hi> From whence it is very plain, and clear that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was no way enclin'd to allow that place unto Worldly Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which of right belongs unto Divine Wiſdom; nor yet to attribute that unto natural Arts and Sciences, which is only peculiar unto the holy Spirit; which thing is alſo further confirm'd in the ſequel of the ſame Chapter, where the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">chap. 2.9, 10, 11, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>nor Ear heard, neither hath it entered into the Heart of Man</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> man in the Fall) <hi>the things which God hath prepared for them that Love him; but God hath revealed them to us by his Spirit, for the Spirit ſearcheth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30541:30"/>all things, yea the deep things of God; for what man knoweth the things of a man, ſave the Spirit of a man which is in him; even ſo the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God;</hi> further adding, <hi>That the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs unto him, neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, if the Lord had intended human Learning, and Arts and Sciences to have been abſolutely neceſſary for the Qualification of a Goſpel Miniſter, its probable he would not only have recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the ſame, &amp; the neceſſity thereof in thoſe reſpects, by ſome of his Servants, but alſo would have choſen more of the Learned Doctors &amp; Rabbies of the times to have been publiſhers of his Mind &amp; Will unto the People in times paſt; but on the contrary, we find very few of thoſe great Doctors that went upon that Errand, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under the Prophetical nor Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſpenſation, but rather the Lord was pleaſed to make uſe of Honeſt, Plain (&amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times) Illiterate People, upon theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts &amp; to call ſeveral from their Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Callings (as the Scriptures bear witneſs) to bear Teſtimony for him, his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30541:30"/>Name and Truth, unto the Sons and Daughters of Men; that ſo the Glory of God, and the excellency of his Wiſdom and Power might more appear in and through ſuch weak Inſtruments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Now if any ſhall object, <hi>That although ſeveral of the Apoſtles were unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when Jeſus called them, yet the Lord made them Learned by a Miracle, before they went abroad to teach all Nations;</hi> and from thence would argue, <hi>That Illiterate People are not fit to preach the Goſpel, nor any but ſuch who by the help of human Learning can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand divers Tongues and Languages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In anſwer thereunto I ſay, That foraſmuch as the Apoſtles were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to go and Teach all Nations, the gift of Tongues was requiſit at that time, and upon that occaſion, to enable them to expreſs themſelves in every Nations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Dialect, that ſo thoſe People to whom they ſpake might the better underſtand what was ſpoken to them; yet it does not follow, that becauſe the gift of Tongues, was expedient for them at that time, in order to render them capable of ſpeaking to the underſtanding of other Nations;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30541:31"/>that therefore they muſt be Learned in other Tongues, who ſpeak only to People of their own Language.</p>
               <p>Yet nevertheleſs, it is not denied but that human Learning, and Art, and Sciences are very uſeful, good and ſervicable in their places, as a right uſe is made thereof, for that People are thereby made more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of managing temporal Affairs, both in reſpect of Merchandize, Trading and other matters; as alſo it may ſo fall out that human Learning, and the knowledg of Tongues and Languages may be uſeful upon ſome accounts, unto ſuch as are or may be called unto the Work and Service of the Goſpel, but then it is in a bleſſed Subordination and Conformity to the Teachings of the Divine Spirit, which is that Golden-Key that opens the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Truth, and inſpires the Soul with a right underſtanding of Spiritual matters, and thoſe People whoſe underſtandings are not opened thereby, be they never ſo Learned or Wiſe, in the Learning or Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the World, yet by reaſon of the blindneſs of their Hearts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18.</note> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ſee not, and Hearing they underſtand not the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Gods Kingdom. Yet ſo it is, that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:30541:31"/>when many People have by natural Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Study, acquired unto ſome knowledg in human Learning, Arts and Sciences, they grow puft up in Mind, wiſe in their own Conceit, and impatient of Contradiction; and ſo are not willing that the uſe of natural Arts and Sciences ſhould be ſo kept within their proper Sphere, as to be limitted unto natural things, and held in a ſubſerviency to the holy Spirit; but ſuch will needs fall a meddling in things of a higher nature, and by the help of human Learning and wordly Wiſdom (without the Revelation and Influence of the Divine Spirit) they will put their meanings upon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and give Expoſitions and Conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon Divine and Spiritual matters, and which is yet worſe, they will often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times attempt the impoſing of their Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon others; and when the Lord is pleaſed to raiſe up any to oppoſe them, then they fall into Paſſion, Wrath, Cruelty, and Perſecution, (the fruits of the Spirit of Error) and upon this occaſion it is that ſo many Conteſts, Diſagreements, Jarrs and Controverſies have riſen among the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Chriſtian Religion, even becauſe Poople have over-valued worldly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30541:32"/>Wiſdom, (which is ſervicable in its place) and under-valued, ſleighted, oppoſed and diſregarded the Teaching, Direction, Counſel, Evidence and Revelation of the Light, Grace and Spirit of Chriſt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which alone can truly open and diſcover the meaning of that which hath proceeded from the ſame Spirit in others;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45.</note> and ſo inſtead of the gracious Influence of the Divine Spirit, they betake themſelves unto human Litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Arts and Sciences, and by their Dark Suggeſtions, Quaint Diſtinctions and Logical Terms, do render things more Obſcure, Intricate and Myſterious, then of themſelves they are; ſo that the World is even burdened with the Volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Tractates, long, tedious and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Diſcourſes about Religious matters; therefore hath it pleaſed God in his infinite Wiſdom and Counſel, in a great meaſure, to lay aſide the Wiſe and Prudent in the Wiſdom of this World, and by his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit to fit and qualifie many weak, mean and contemptible Inſtruments, in the Eyes of men, and make uſe of them for the publiſhing of his pure and naked Truth, that ſo it might be freed of thoſe Miſts and Foggs wherewith thoſe Linguiſts
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30541:32"/>have clouded it, and that People might be directed to wait for that univerſal Spirit which, as it is received, doth opperate in the Hearts and Souls of People, in order to work out Sin and Iniquity, raiſe up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to newneſs of Life, and to give People an underſtanding in Divine and Spiritual matters; that ſo they may be thereby fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, prepared and qualified for perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Pure and Spiritual Worſhip, which is acceptable unto God in this Goſpel day.</p>
               <p>And further, ſuch hath been the good pleaſure of our God in times paſt, as alſo in this our day, not only, in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to lay aſide the Wiſe and Prudent of the World, upon theſe accounts, but alſo to ſet aſide, as unneceſſary for the Goſpel Miniſtry, thoſe long tedious Books, Diſcourſes and Comments which have been and are the product of worldly Wiſdom, and the fruit of mans natural and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed Mind and Spirit, and the Lord by his own Wiſdom, Spirit and Power doth aid, furniſh, aſſiſt and ſupply every true Goſpel Miniſter in the performance of his Duty and Service, both as to matter what, the time when, and the Perſons to whom; thus doth he in his heavenly Counſel order and diſpoſe the Spirits of his People ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30541:33"/>for every Occaſion and Service that they are called unto, as there is a true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon him: So that the very riſe of their Services is not ſimply from human Abilities, but from the divine Gift; as the Apoſtle very well obſerved, <hi>As every man hath received the Gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, as good Stewards of the manifold Grace of God; if any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God; if any man miniſter, let him do it as of the ability which God giveth, that God in all things may be glorified, through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.10, 11. Again the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> writeth thus, <hi>Having then Gifts differing according to the Grace that is given to us, whether Propheſie, let us Propheſie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proportion of Faith; or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, les us wait on our Miniſtring; or he that Teacheth, on Teaching; or he that Exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, on Exhortation,</hi> Rom. 12.6, 7, 8. From whence it is yet further clearly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that the riſe and foundation of true Goſpel Performances, ſtands not in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſdom, or human Arts and Sciences, but in the Gift and Grace of God, revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and manifeſted in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:30541:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Section IX.</hi> Concerning outward Force and Violence in Religious matters, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs of forceable reſiſting the temporal Magiſtracy.</head>
               <p>AGain, as thoſe who do truly miniſter from this divine Gift, endeavour not to fill Peoples Ears and Minds with ſtrange, uncertain and fore-prepared Arguments, Loud Diſcourſes, Dark Suggeſtions, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Terms, Philoſophical Notions and Conceptions about Divine and Spiritual matters: Neither do they endeavour to force or enjoyn People to receive them and their Teſtimony, whether they will or no; but in all Chriſtian Meekneſs, Plainneſs, Gentleneſs, Forbearance and Sincerity they declare and hold forth the Truth of God, as they have received it, and do recommend their Teſtimony <hi>unto every mans Conſcience in the ſight of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.2. which thing is agreeable to the practice of Jeſus Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Servants in the Primitive times. We ſee with what plainneſs in Speech and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:30541:34"/>Similies and Parables our Lord did expreſs himſelf to the People, as appears in the writings of the Evangeliſts, and how tenderly he invited People to come unto him, and learn of him that was meek and low in Heart,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28, 29.</note> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing they ſhould find reſt unto their Souls; yea, and when the <hi>Jews</hi> (notwithſtanding his great inclination to gather them) did continue in hardneſs and rebellion againſt him, and his heavenly Meſſage, yet he Wept over them, as we read <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41, 42. <hi>And when he was come near he beheld the City, and Wept over it, ſaying, if thou hadſt known, even thou at the leaſt, in this thy day, the things which belong unto thy Peace! but now they are hid from thy Eyes.</hi> And yet as a further demonſtration of the Love, Meekneſs and Gentleneſs of his Spirit, we have an account that when ſomething of ſharpneſs appeared in ſome of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, againſt thoſe <hi>Samaritanes</hi> who recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them not, we may perceive how ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly he rebuked them, ſaying, <hi>Ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 9.54, 55, 56.</note> 
                  <hi>for the Son of Man is not come to deſtroy Mens Lifes, but to ſave them.</hi> It is alſo further manifeſt in the Scriptures, that the Apoſtles and Servants
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:30541:34"/>of Chriſt did all along proceed, upon Truth's account, in much plainneſs of Speech, Gentleneſs, Humility, Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial and Chriſtian Forbearance towards all People. The which ſaid Practice of theirs, upon theſe accounts, may ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve for a Confutation unto ſuch as will needs pretend to the Chriſtian Faith, and to be Miniſters, Servants and Followers of Chriſt, and are ſtrangely Leavened and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with many Peeviſh, Proud, Stingy; Inſolent, Covetous, Unmortified, Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting and Naughty Humors and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, no way agreeable to the nature and tendency of the Goſpel of Peace, nor to that pure, holy and undefiled Religion which was Inſtituted by our Lord, and Practiced by his Diſciples and Followers.</p>
               <p>As outward Force, Severity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion in Religious matters does no way ſeem to be conſiſtent with <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> ſo neither do we find any Precept or Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for it in the writings of the New Teſtament: That which ſome would alledge in vindication thereof, is the ſaying of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23. <hi>Go out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the High-Ways and Hedges and compel them to come in, that my Houſe may be filled.</hi> But if this ſaying of his be rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:30541:35"/>and compared with other Texts of Scripture, there will no ſuch thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, as that he intended to propagate the Goſpel of Peace by outward Force and Severity; as for the words <hi>Compel</hi> and <hi>Conſtrain,</hi> they are much what Synonymous, and do not always import outward Force, Violence or Compulſion, but many times in the Scriptures friendly Invitations, kind Intreaties, undeniable and demonſtrable Reaſons, and gentle Perſwaſions, which are moſt agreeable to the meekneſs and gentleneſs of that Spirit by which the true Miniſters, and Servants of Chriſt, have been, are, and ought to be acted in all their proceedings upon the Truths account: We read that when <hi>Jeſus</hi> appeared unto thoſe two Diſciples, that were going to <hi>Emmaus, When they drew nigh to the Village, he made as though he would have gone further, but they conſtrained him, and he went in to tarry with them.</hi> There is no queſtion but this conſtraint was by fair meanes, even by a kind entreaty, as the Text expreſſeth, <hi>[Abide with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s]</hi> and reaſon was alſo ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for it, <hi>becauſe it was towards Evening, and the Day was far ſpent,</hi> Luke 24.28, 29. Again its ſaid, <hi>Jeſus conſtrained his Diſciples to get into a Ship,</hi> Mat. 14.22. And we
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30541:35"/>read, that when <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Heart was open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhe conſtrained <hi>Paul</hi> and his Company to come into her Houſe and abide there, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15. Alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Speech to <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, <hi>Why compelleſt thou the</hi> Gentiles <hi>to Live as do the</hi> Jews? <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.14. All which ſaid Expreſſions, concerning Compulſion or Conſtraint, do no way ſeem to hold out any thing of outward Force, Violence or Severity; But rather earneſt Intreaty, kind, gentle or ſtrong Perſwaſions of Reaſon, Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet further if we conſider the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and tendency of that Diſcourſe, wherein the word <hi>Compel</hi> is made uſe of, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23. there will no ſuch thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, as that any outward Force or Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence was intened by that Expreſſion, the Parable is of a certain man that made a Supper, and bad many Gueſts, &amp; they urge excuſes, and come not; the Maſter of the Houſe being angry, bids his Servant go out into the Streets and Lanes of the City, and bring in the Poor, the Maimed, the Halt and the Blind; &amp; that being done, and ſtill room for more; the Maſter ſends again, ſaying, <hi>Go out into the High-Ways, and Hedges, and compel them to come in, that my Houſe may be filled.</hi> Now conſider, if we
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:30541:36"/>take the Parable literally, as it is, what manner of Force or Compulſion was either needful or proper to be uſed to ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are here mentioned? it is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to force Gueſts to a Feaſt, nor puniſh them if they come not; neither is it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſuch Perſons as had no better Proviſion then they could get from the High-Ways and Hedges ſhould need any outward Force, Violence or Compulſion to bring them to a good Supper; if they were deſtitute of Succour and Relief, a gentle and loving invitation to a Feaſt, and encouragements of being kindly Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd were ſufficient reaſons to compel them to go. And alſo, if we conſider it in aſpiritual ſence, the like reaſon will hold good any way; for we can no way conceive that there is any occaſion of uſing outward Force of Compulſion to cauſe thoſe that are ſpiritually poor, &amp; in want, to receive inward Help and Succour, their Neceſſities will ſufficiently enduce them to accept it, without any violent or forceable treating.</p>
               <p>Further more as the Servants of Chriſt, and People of God, ought not by any outward Compulſion to force People to receive their Teſtimony, and embrace
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30541:36"/>their Religion, whether they will or no: So on the other hand, if thoſe in publick Authority, who are concern'd in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this World, ſhall happen to Moleſt, Trouble and Perſecute them, for and upon the account of the exerciſe of their Conſciences towards God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by endeavour to force them to deny their Religion, and to embrace another; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſuch Perſecutors do greatly Err in ſuch practices, yet it does no way appear to be conſiſtant with Chriſtianity for thoſe who are Perſecuted, upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, to make any publick Reſiſtance by outward Force or Violence; but they ought patiently to ſuffer what Afflictions the Lord is pleaſed to permit to come upon them in thoſe Caſes: which thing is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt by the Example of our Lord Jeſus, as alſo by the Doctrine and Practice of his Apoſtles. We read that when our Lord Jeſus was apprehended by the <hi>Jews,</hi> one of thoſe that were with him drew his Sword, and ſmote a Servant of the high Prieſt, but Jeſus was ſo far from encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging People in ſuch actions that he had him put up his Sword in its Place, ſaying, <hi>All they that take the Sword, ſhall periſh with the Sword,</hi> Mat. 26.51, 52, 53. There's
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30541:37"/>no queſtion, but if our Lord had ſeen it requiſit to have made forceable Reſiſtance, he might have prayed the Father and have had Legions of Angels to have aſſiſted him; but he was other wiſe diſpoſed, <hi>When he was Reviled, he Reviled not again; When he Suffered, he threatned not, but committed himſelf to him that judgeth Righteouſly,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.23. Alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> gives an account how they behaved themſelves in theſe Caſes; <hi>Being Reviled</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we Bleſs; being Perſecuted, we ſuffer it; being Defamed we Intreat; we are made as the filth of the World, and are (accounted as) the off ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all things, unto this day,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.12, 13. Again the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Avenge not your ſelves, but rather give place unto Wrath; for it is written, Vengeance is mine, I will repay, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Rom. 12.19. <hi>The Weapons of the Saints warfare were not Carnal,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.4. <hi>Neither did they wreſtle with Fleſh and Blood,</hi> Epheſ. 6.12. But in all Chriſtian Patience, Meekneſs and Self-denial they were willing to bear the Reproches and Contradictions of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men, and that for the ſake of him in whom they had believed; <hi>Preces &amp; Lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae,</hi> Prayers and Tears were the Arms they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:30541:37"/>uſed upon theſe accounts; and thoſe that ſuffer thus, according to the will of God, were to commit the keeping of their Souls unto him, in well-doing, as unto a faithful Creator, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. and herein was their Peace and Safety.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section X.</hi> Concerning the Maintenance of Goſpel Miniſters.</head>
               <p>FOraſmuch as thoſe whoſe Miniſtry doth proceed from the Grace and Spirit of God, do not Force or Compel People to receive their Teſtimony, whether they will or no; neither do they go about to Force or Compel any to Maintain them, but as they are Goſpel Miniſters, they are content with a Goſpel allowance. We read, that when our Lord ſent forth his Diſciples to preach the Kingdom of Heaven at hand, amongſt other things that he gave them in charge, he ſays unto them, <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give,</hi> Mat. 10.8. <hi>And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whatſoever City ye enter, and they receive you, Eat ſuch things as are ſet before you,</hi> Luke 10.8. <hi>And whoſoever ſhall not receive you, nor hear your Words, when you depart
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30541:38"/>out of that Houſe, or City, ſhake off the duſt of your Feet,</hi> &amp;c. Mat. 10.14. From whence divers things are to be obſerved, <hi>Firſt,</hi> What the Diſciples had to Preach, they had freely received it. <hi>Secondly,</hi> They were not to require Wages for Preaching, but to do it freely. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They were to eat ſuch things as were ſet before them, only where they were received. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They were to be ſo far from being cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourous for Relief of them that did not receive them, that they were not to ſuffer the duſt of their City to cleave to them, but to wipe it off againſt them. And as this was the way of Maintenance and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, that was appointed by our Lord for ſuch as were ſent forth to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; ſo we no where find that the Apoſtles or Servants of Chriſt did act contrary thereunto, ſo as to force any, by outward Compulſion, to maintain them whether they would or no; for that would have been quite contrary to the way of Chriſt, and to the nature of that Religion which he Inſtituted.</p>
               <p>And if ſo then it was unlawful for thoſe whom Chriſt immediately ſent to preach the Goſpel, outwardly to force or compel any either to receive their Teſtimony, or
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30541:38"/>Maintain them, I hope few will deny but that it is much more unlawful for thoſe, whom Chriſt never ſent, to claim any ſuch priviledge.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Tythes,</hi> which many of thoſe who now pretend to be Goſpel Miniſters will needs claim, and which many of them do Sue, Trouble, Moleſt and Impriſon their peaceable Neighbours about; we do no where find them appointed in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the New Teſtament as due to the Goſpel Miniſtry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 'Tis true, in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Old Teſtament,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.</note> we find that God did chuſe <hi>Aaron</hi> &amp; his Sons for the office of the Prieſthood, and he did alſo chuſe the reſt of the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> for the ſervice of the Tabernacle, and gave them the tenth in <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their Service; thoſe <hi>Levites</hi> were to offer up a Heave Offering to the Lord out of their Tythe, and were to give it to <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt, for himſelf and his Sons; and this was all the ſhare which we find the Legal Prieſt to have appointed him in Tythes, even the tenth of the tenth, and that from the hand of the <hi>Levites;</hi> moreover, thoſe Tythes were only due and payable, by Gods appointment, from the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> unto the <hi>Levites</hi> of that Land, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:30541:39"/>that becauſe the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> had no other Inheritance allotted them there, among their Brethren.</p>
               <p>But now it is to be obſerv'd that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath by offering up himſelf, as a Lamb without ſpot unto God, put an end unto that Legal Prieſthood, and Service which received Tythes, and blotted out the hand-writing of Ordinances againſt us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14.</note> nailing it to his Croſs; and hath inſtituted a Worſhip and Service more pure and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual then that which was performed under the Diſpenſation of the Law. We do no where find that he has either limited Tythes, or any other ſtinted maintenance for the Goſpel Miniſtry, but has left that as a free and voluntary Act of thoſe that did own and receive his Meſſengers and Servants, urging this, <hi>The Work-man is worthy of his Meat.</hi> And truly ſo he is: Thoſe who receive Spirituals from the Servants of Chriſt, will no doubt be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to communicate Temporals unto them, (that is ſo much as is needful for them.) They are not to mind high things,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.8.</note> nor to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> after great Places and Preferments, Annual Stipends, Sallaries and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30541:39"/>Augmentations, nor yet deſiſt, or let fall their Teſtimony, for want of a ſetled Maintenance, but having Food and Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are there with to be content; and ſo to proceed as the Lord ſhall make way for them, truſting him with the care of their Bodies as well as of their Souls. And truly thoſe who according to the Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtle do thus caſt their care upon God upon theſe accounts ſhall not want,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10</note> becauſe he careth for them, &amp; will open the Hearts of thoſe, unto whom they Miniſter that ſo they may relieve them, according to their Neceſſities; and thus the Lord is known and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be the Author of their Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as well as of their Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>That which ſome would alledge to prove a forced and ſtinted Maintenance for the Goſpel Miniſtry, is the ſaying of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7, 9, 11, 13, 14. which being rightly conſidered, does no way hold out any ſuch thing as a forced, or ſtinted Maintenance; the Apoſtle in the 4th verſe remembers the Words of Chriſt, and ſays, <hi>Have we not power to Ear and to Drink?</hi> &amp;c. and then in the 7th verſe he ands, <hi>Who goeth a Warfare at any time at his own Charge? Who planteth a Vineyard and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:30541:40"/>eateth not of the Fruit thereof? Or who feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Flock, and eateth not of the Milk of the Flock?</hi> &amp;c. Theſe Texts of Scripturce do not at all encourage a forced Maintenance, nor altogether ſet forth what the Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is, but rather who they are from whom it is to be received; conſider at whoſe charge ought the Souldier to go a warfare, but at his or theirs for whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence he Fights? He that plants a Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard may eat of the Fruit, but it muſt be of Fruit thereof: He that feeds a Flock may eat of the Milk, but it muſt be of the Milk of the Flock which he feeds: The Ox that trod out the Corn was not to be muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but to be feed by him whoſe Corn he trod out; bet it was not agreable to the equity of the Law, that while the Ox trod out Corn for one man, another ſhould be fore'd to keep him; <hi>If,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we have ſowen unto you ſpiritual things, is it a great thing if we ſhall reap your carnal things?</hi> 1 Cor. 9.11. No it is no great thing, for if he had ſowen unto them, and they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of him, he might by Chriſt appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment expect to receive of them.</p>
               <p>Again he ſays, <hi>They which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> Yes they may ſo, and ought to be content with it;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:30541:40"/>but then this does not argue, that they ſhall live of the Law, or that any under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Goſpel Maintenance ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon <hi>Chriſtians</hi> the Bondage of a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical</hi> Inſtitution, viz. the exaction of Tythes, or any other forced Maintenance; for that although Tythes were due by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet they were terminated with the Service they were given for, and there is no appearance of any ground for any to claim them by vertue of any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Authority. As for the Words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> above recited, they do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to no more then this, That Goſpel Miniſters may receive a Goſpel Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, from ſuch as receive them and their Doctrine, but not from ſuch as receive them not, nor do own their Miniſtry; and what this Goſpel Maintenance is we find it plainly ſet forth by Chriſt himſelf, in his Speech to his Diſciples, <hi>Eat ſuch things as are ſet before you: Eat and Drink ſuch things as they give, for the Workman is worthy of his Meat,</hi> Mat. 10.10. Luke 10.7. By which Expreſſions we may conceive that the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conveniencies of Life are intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and to be underſtood.</p>
               <p>And yet for a further confirmation of our Sence and Judgment in theſe reſpects,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:30541:41"/>we may conſider what the practice of the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt were in the primitive times, and what they exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted others unto upon theſe accounts: We find that when the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had told the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> how that a neceſſity was laid upon him, yea wo was unto him if he preacht not the Goſpel; he puts the Queſtion,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>What is my Reward then?</hi> and anſwers it ſaying, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily that when I preach the Goſpel, I may make the Goſpel of Chriſt without Charge.</hi> Alſo the ſame Apoſtle, when he took his leave of the Elders of the Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> thus expreſſeth himſelf, <hi>I have coveted no mans Silver, or Gold, or Apparel, ye your ſelves know that theſe Hands have miniſtred unto my neceſſities, and to them that were with me; I have ſhewed you all things, how that ſo labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ye ought to ſupport the Weak, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the words of the Lord Jeſus, It is more bleſſed to give then to receive.</hi> From whence we may obſerve, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That he was ſo far from any eager perſuit after worldly Wealth, great Benefits and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, that he ſays, He coveted no mans Gold, Silver nor Apparel. <hi>Secondly,</hi> His own Hands had miniſtred to his Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and them that were with him: By
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30541:41"/>which it appears that he was not inclin'd to Idleneſs, in expectation to be maintain'd out of other mens Labours, but he wrought with his own Hands, as he intimates him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, &amp; as alſo appears <hi>Acts</hi> 18.1, 2, 3. Being a Tent-maker by Occupation. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He does not at all encourage them in Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but on the contrary tells them, That ſo labouring (<hi>viz.</hi> as he had done) they ought to ſupport the Weak, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the words of Jeſus, It is more bleſſed to give then to receive. And again the ſame Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.7, 8. writeth thus, <hi>For your ſelves know, how ye ought to follow us; for we behaved not our ſelves diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly among you; neither did we eat any mans Bread for nought; but wrought with Labour and Travel Night and Day, that we might not be chargable to any of you.</hi> Likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> in his Exhortation to the Elders, ſays unto them, <hi>Feed the Flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly, not for filthy Lucre, but of a ready mind; neither as being Lords ever Gods Heritage, but being enſamples to the Flock,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.1, 2, 3. By all which recited Paſſages, it is plainly manifeſt, that the Apoſtles had a great eate not to be burdenſome to any, and that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:30541:42"/>the Goſpel of Chriſt might be preſerved without Charge; they were ſo far from compelling or forcing a Maintenance, from ſuch as did not own nor receive them, that they forbore to make uſe of that Power which Chriſt allowed them, even among ſuch as did receive them. It ſeems the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> wrought with his Hands (when he had an oportunity) and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Brethren to be followers of him, and mark them that walk ſo as they had them for an enſample,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17.</note> and there is ſmall queſtion but the reſt of the Apoſtles were like-minded with him: We ſee that <hi>Peter</hi> is ſo far from allowing the Elders to act by Conſtraint, or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon great Wages and Revenues for their Service, that he quite oppoſes it in theſe words, <hi>Not by Conſtraint, not for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Lucre,</hi> obſerve the Epithite that he beſtowes upon <hi>Lucre,</hi> nothing leſs then <hi>Filthy:</hi> It ſeems he look't upon it as a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thing, for ſuch as were to Feed and Nouriſh the Flock of God, and to take the overſight thereof, that their Hearts and Minds ſhould be ſo bent upon worldly Preferments, and exerciſed in covetous Practices, as to do what they did for filthy Lucre ſake; therefore he doth with much
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:30541:42"/>ſharpneſs enlarge upon that matter, in his ſecond Chapter of his ſecond Epiſtle, as may be there ſeen at large.</p>
               <p>Thus as it was the way of the Miniſters and Servants of Chriſt in the primitive times, to act according to the Precepts and Directions of our bleſſed Lord, and to adviſe and exhort others thereunto, and alſo to bear 'Teſtimony againſt ſuch as tranfgreſs upon theſe accounts; ſo alſo it highly concerns all thoſe who pretend to be Miniſters of Chriſt in this our day, to ſearch and try their ways, and in the Light of Chriſt ſeriouſly to weigh and examine the matter, whether they be truly called, qualified and acted by the Spirit of Chriſt yea or nay? if they be, no queſtion but they will manifeſt the ſame in Humility, Meekneſs, Self-denial, Chriſtian-forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Charity and Doctrine; as alſo in acting according to the Directions of Chriſt, and Practice of his People: But on the contrary, if any under that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence be found in a Proud, Lordly, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and Perſecuting Spirit, walking in the ſteps of thoſe whom the true Prophets and Servants of Chriſt have always teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied againſt; it greatly behoves all People to beware of them, according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30541:43"/>of our bleſſed Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15, 16. <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets, which come to you in Sheeps clothing, but inwardly they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ning Wolves; ye ſhall know them by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uits.</hi> Foraſmuch as they have a ſhew of Chriſtianity, and ſo thereby are clothed with Sheeps clothing, but being inwardly departed from the pure, holy, meek and peaceable Spirit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, they endeavour to Perſecute, Tear and Devour them that are not willing to Feed and Relieve them, and ſo therein they are ravening Wolves. I do not hereby place any particular charge upon any, but leave every one to ſee and know by their Fruits, deſiring that all thoſe who are under thoſe Circumſtances and Qualities may come to Repentance, and amendment of Life, whilſt the day of their Viſitation laſteth; otherwiſe all their pretences to Chriſtianity, or the miniſterial Function, will not reſcue them in that day, when the Righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth, doth recompence every one according to their Deeds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:30541:43"/>
               <head>Section XI. <hi>Concerning PRAYER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat now which yet further remains to be conſidered, is thoſe other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Services which are to be done and performed by true Believers, either in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate or in their publick Aſſemblies; and upon this account ſhall mention that of <hi>Prayer,</hi> which is very neceſſary for the People of God to be found in the practice of, being a duty incumbent upon us, and frequently commanded and exhorted unto in the holy Scriptures, and as it is neceſſary for all thoſe who are concerned in the Church of Chriſt, in publick Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Declarations, to be ſupplied and aſſiſted in thoſe Services by the Grace and Spirit of Chriſt; even ſo, alſo it is by the help and influence of the ſame Spirit, that the People of God are enabled to pray acceptably unto him, and without the help thereof, in ſome degree or other, true Prayer cannot be performed.</p>
               <p>That the Spirit of Chriſt is abſolutely neceſſary upon this account is clear even
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:30541:44"/>from the words of Chriſt, <hi>Without me ye can do nothing</hi>— Alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Spirit alſo helpeth our Infirmities, for we know not what me ſhould pray for as we ought, but the Spirit it ſelf maketh Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for us, with Sighs &amp; Groans that cannot be uttered; and he that ſearcheth the Hearts knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, becauſe be maketh Interceſſion for the Saints, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God,</hi> Rom. 8.26, 27. Again, <hi>Praying always, with all Prayer and Supplication in the Spirit, and watching there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, with all perſeverance and Supplication for all Saints,</hi> Epheſ. 6.18. And alſo in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians, I will pray with the Spirit, and with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.15. From whence ſeveral things are obſervable, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Gods People can do nothing that's acceptable unto him, without Chriſt, and the help of his Spirit. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That of themſelves they know not what to pray for as they ought. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That it is the Spirit which helpeth ſuch Infirmities, and maketh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion unto God for his People <hi>Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> The way and manner of the Spirits In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, with Sighs and Groans that cannot be uttered. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That God graciouſly receives the Prayers of ſuch as
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:30541:44"/>are offered and preſented unto him by the Spirit, foraſmuch as Interceſſion is thereby made for them, according to the will of God. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The Apoſtle, being ſenſible of the acceptance, and prevalency of ſuch Prayers, doth exhort the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to pray always, with all Prayer and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication in the Spirit, and to watch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto withall Perſeverance. <hi>Seventhly,</hi> He gives an account how he himſelf will pray, ſaying, <hi>I will pray with the Spirit, and with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus then, as the Prayers of ſuch who wait for, and receive <hi>Divine Aſſiſtance,</hi> do obtain <hi>Divine Acceptance;</hi> ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the Prayers of wicked and ungodly men, who receive not, nor expect any ſuch ſpiritual help, but are acted by the Spirit of Error and Vanity, can no way be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God, nor beneficial to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The Scriptures do afford us divers Teſtimonies to this purpoſe; <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>If I regard Iniquity in my Heart the Lord will not hear me,</hi> Pſal. 66.18. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>The Sacrifice of the Wicked is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 15.8. And again, <hi>He that turneth his Ear from the Law, even his Prayer ſhall be abomination.</hi> Alſo the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ſaith to the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:30541:45"/>People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that had forſaken the Lord, and rebelled againſt his Spirit, and ſo become a ſinful Nation,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2, 3.13.</note> 
                  <hi>When ye ſpread forth your Hands I will hide mine Eyes from you, yea when you make many Prayers I will not hear, your Hands are full of Blood.</hi> Again, we read <hi>John</hi> 9.31. <hi>We know that God heareth not Sinners, but of any be a worſhipper of God, and doth his will, him heareth.</hi> And alſo 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. <hi>The Eyes of the Lord are over the Righteous, and his Ears are open to their Prayers, but the Face of the Lord is againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that do Evil.</hi> Thus it is plain that the Prayers and Sacrifices of Wicked and Sinful men have not been acceptable unto God, (which they remain'd in that ſtate) but rather an abomination unto him, being not offered in ſincerity of Heart, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a right diſpoſition of Soul and Spirit.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> of old thought it ſufficient for them if they did but pay their daily Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and offer their cuſtomary Oblations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from thence concluding all was well; but it prov'd not ſo, for the Lord by the Prophet asks them, To what purpoſe was the multitude of their? Sacrifices? and bids them bring no more vain Oblations: <hi>Incenſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is an abomination unto me,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:30541:45"/>the new Moons and Sabbaths, the calling of Aſſemblies is Iniquity, even the ſolemn Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> And again, by the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> he ſays, <hi>Though you offer me Burnt Offerings, and Meat Offerings, I will not accept them; neither will I regard the Peace Offerings of your fat Beaſts.</hi> And what was the reaſon of all this diſlike? Even becauſe the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were Wicked and Sinful; Therefore he ſays, <hi>Waſh ye, make ye Clean, put away the evil of your doings from before my Eyes, ceaſe to do Evil, learn to do Well, ſeek Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, relieve the Oppreſſed, judge the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, and plead for the Widow.</hi> And then no queſtion but they might be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>As it was with the <hi>Jews</hi> in that ſtate, ſo its probable the caſe may be with many of thoſe call'd <hi>Chriſtians</hi> now, who think is ſufficient for them to be preſent at the reading over of Morning and Evening Prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the common Form and Cuſtom; and yet do not rightly conſider that their Hearts are polluted and deiled with Sin and Iniquity, which no queſtion will block up their way from Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine acceptance, as well as it did unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old. As for Sin it is a thing that cannot be Chriſten'd, neither will the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:30541:46"/>Righteous God own it in any, let their pretence be what it will. It has always been the cauſe of mans Wo and Miſery, and of his Separation from God in all Ages; and its the ſame now where People remain in it, and continue Impenitent and in Rebellion againſt the Reproofs and Counſel of the Light and Spirit of Chriſt in themſelves; <hi>Your Iniquities</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>have ſeparated between you and your God; and your Sins have hid his Face from you, that he will not hear,</hi> Iſa 59.2. <hi>They ſhall call upon me</hi> (ſaith Wiſdom) <hi>but I will not anſwer; they ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall not find me,</hi> Prov. 1.28. It is not ſimply the calling upon God, or making mention of his bleſſed Name that gains acceptance with him, or draws down his bleſſings upon men; but it is a calling upon him in Faith, and in a rightly ordered and well-diſpoſed. Mind and Spirit, <hi>For unto this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n will I look (ſaith the Lord), even to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is Poor and of a contrite Spirit, and trembleth at my Word,</hi> Iſa 66.2. Again, <hi>The Lord is nigh to all that call upon him in Truth, he will fulfill the deſire of them that fear him, he alſo will hear their cry and will ſave them; the Lord preſerveth all them that Love him, but the Wicked will he Deſtroy,</hi> Pſal. 145, 18, 19, 20.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:30541:46"/>
               <p>Howbeit ſtill although the Prayers of Wicked and Sinfull Men, whilſt they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in Impenitency and Rebellion againſt God, are not acceptable unto him; yet nevertheleſs ſuch as are polluted with Sin and Iniquity, and do come to be ſecretly touch, &amp; awaken'd by the Light and Spirit of Chriſt, and are bowed down under the ſence of their own Sinfulneſs, unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Miſery, Weakneſs for Inability, ſuch looking up to God, and inwardly breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, ſecret Deſires and Aſpirations, or uttering Words in Prayer and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation unto him for help and deliverance from under the bondage of Sin and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; the Lord God in his own due time will undoubtedly hear and anſwer the deſires of ſuch: But ſtill this does no, way admit that wicked and ungodly men are capable of praying acceptably, any otherwiſe then as they are toucht, awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and helpt by the Spirit of Chriſt, and being truly bowed down under the ſence of God goodneſs, and their own unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thneſs, are led to Repentance, and ſo by the grace of God are drawn to ſupplicate his Name for Help and Deliverance. We read that when the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> exhorted <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer unto Prayer, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> places
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:30541:47"/>Repentance before it, ſaying, <hi>Repent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of this thy wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thy Heart may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given thee,</hi> Acts 8.22. Again, <hi>Repent ye therefore, and be Converted, that your Sins may be blotted out, when the times of refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord,</hi> Acts 3.19. From whence it is obſervable, That as Repentance doth go before Prayer, ſo alſo doth Repentance and Converſion go before blotting out of Sin. Now as to the Prayers of thoſe who are high and lofty in Mind and Spirit, and take delight in Sin and Ungodlineſs, and to ſpend their precious time in Vanity, Folly and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and alſo of thoſe who may ſeem outwardly to be more demure, yet ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually reſt in the gall of Bitterneſs againſt the Truth, and in the bond of Iniquity, there may ſeem to be little defference of their Devotions in the ground as to Divine acceptance, ſo long as both ſorts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple remain in Impenitency; for the firſt can turn out of their vain Converſation, or however ſuſpend the outward act there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for a little ſeaſon; and the other their worldly Diſcourſe, and ſo fall to repeat ſome few words of Prayer in a formal and cuſtomary way, and immediately again,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:30541:47"/>even as ſoon as ever the words to God are out of their Mouths (without any true regard to the Greatneſs and Majeſty of him to whom they have even been making Supplication) they'l fall on again upon their former Diſcourſe, and many times (as hath been obſerv'd) upon Vain, Idle and Prophane Talk; ſo that without any diſtinction or waiting for divine help to perform their Duties to God, they appear to be acted by one and the ſame Spirit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both accounts: Certainly! If there be any ſuch thing as vain Oblations and Prayers that God regardeth not, (as no queſtion but there is) thoſe Prayers and Devotions which are thus begun, carried on, and concluded in mans own natural Will, Strength and Wiſdom (without the help and influence of the Grace and Spirit of Chriſt) are of that number.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Its probable ſome may alledge, <hi>That our Lord taught his Diſciples to Pray, and gave them a Form of Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In anſwer whereunto I ſay, That although he did ſo, yet they were in ſome ſort Diſciples before he taught them, (not worldly men) and his teaching them
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:30541:48"/>at that time is not an argument that every one, in their own will and time, can ſay that Prayer acceptably, but we may rather infer from thence, That as they then were not to pray as the Hypocrites and Heathen did, but according as he taught them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then outwardly preſent with them; even ſo his People are not to pray now as the Hypocrites and Heathen do, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as he teaches them being ſpiritually preſents with them; yet nevertheleſs that Prayer which he taught them, as it was then, ſo it is now very good and uſeful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch as can expreſs thoſe Words, there ſet forth, in Truth and Righteouſneſs: Thoſe who have received the adoption of Sons, by vertue of the holy Spirit, have right to call God Father, and may ſay in Truth, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name, thy Kingdom come, thy Will be done, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Earth as it is in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. But on the contrary, How can thoſe who are Children of Wrath, and ſubject to the power of Darkneſs, truly call God Father? How can they who are altogether unholy hallow the Name of God? What will it avan ſuch to tell of the coming of Gods Kingdom, who daily rebel againſt that which would give an entrance thereunto? How can thoſe do
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:30541:48"/>the will of God in Earth, who neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that which would enable them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, nor will believe that any ſuch thing an be done? Thus al tho wicke ungodly men may tell of Prayer, yet in that ſtate they are quite out of order, and utterly uncapable of performing it acceptably, until they have received the Spirit, and have the help and influence thereof, in ſome degree or other; which thing yet leads me to this further obſervation, If no man can call Jeſus Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt, as the Apoſtle poſitively affirms, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. Then how can any truly call God Father, but as they are in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure acted by the Spirit of the Son.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, I would have none to ſuſpect that I do in the leaſt intend hereby to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage People in being diligent in Prayer and Supplication unto God Almighty, but I would Caution and Exhort them, in the Light of Chriſt, to wait for the help and influence of his Grace and Spirit in ſuch undertakings, that ſo they may be enabled to perform thoſe Duties acceptably, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore words be uttered unto the Lord, let it firſt be conſidered how the Heart is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and from what root the words do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, for it is not ſimply the words, but
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:30541:49"/>the riſe thereof that the Lord looks at in all our Services and Devotions before him. And as thoſe that fail in the Foundation do hazard the Superſtructure; even ſo where People fall wrong in the very ground of their Devotions, their further proceedings therein will be in danger to prove Inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant and Unſucceſsful. I do not ſay but that God, who is rich in Mercy and waits to be gracious unto People, doth and will paſs by many Weakneſſes and Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon theſe accounts, yet none ought ſo to preſume thereon, as to make the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular acts of Gods Love and Condeſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto ſome, and upon ſome accounts, to be a general rule for all, or to be an excuſe or cover unto any for Diſobedience and Rebellion; it is certainly the duty of all to be diligent in Prayer and Supplication unto God, and I cannot but exhort all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thereunto; but then it does not follow that any ſhall attempt ſuch performances, or go about the ſame being unprepared by the Spirit of God, for that thereby, if they have been negligent in Prayer before, they will be ſo far from mending the matter, that they will incur a freſh cenſure; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let it be the care of every one, that goes about to perform the duty of Prayer,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:30541:49"/>to watch and wait upon God diligently, for the help and concurrence of his bleſſed and holy Spirit in all ſuch undertakings; and alſo when they feel and witneſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be rightly diſpoſed in Spirit for approaching before the Lord in Prayer and Supplication unto him, let them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider themſelves in his preſence, and be careful to appear in an humble and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent poſture of Body, as well as Soul, (that is) in a decent, orderly and comely man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as much as well can be, with bowed Knees,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4.</note> and men with uncovered Heads, (according to the Practice and Direction of the Apoſtle in thoſe caſes) thereby ſhewing forth that holy Submiſſion, Reverence and Reſpect every way, which we all owe to the Divine Majeſtly, unto whom all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Glory and Praiſe is due, world without end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:30541:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Section XII.</hi> Concerning Singing of Pſſalms, and Artiſſcial Muſick.</head>
               <p>THe next thing to be conſidered is <hi>Singing of Pſſalmes,</hi> which is confeſt to be a part of Gods Worſhip, and very acceptable as it proceeds from a true ſence of God Love in the Heart and ariſes from the influence of the holy Spirit, whereby the Lords People are led to breath forth unto God in a ſweet and ſpiritual Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or in Words ſutable to their preſent Condition; but then on the contrary, when vain minded People do go about to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in their own will and time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al, ſeigned and cuſtomary way, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> having the knowledge of the motion and concurrence of the Divine Spirit, and Word of Life in the Heart, ſuch Singing can no way be acceptable unto God, nor beneficial unto thoſe that uſe it; for as it was in the caſe of Preaching and Praying ſo it is in this of Singing, the holy Spirit is to be the chief and principal Author, Mover and Actor in theſe reſpect.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:30541:50"/>
               <p>Which thing will yet further appear, if we conſider the Words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> upon this account, <hi>Be not drunk with Wine, wherein is exceſs, but be filled with the Spirit, Speaking to your ſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, Singing and making Melody unto the Lord,</hi> Epheſ 5. 18, 19. And again, <hi>Let the Word of Chriſt dwell in you richly in all Wiſdom, Teaching and Admoniſhing one another in Pſalms, and Hymns and ſpiritual Songs, ſinging with Grace in your Hearts to the Lord,</hi> Col. 3.16. From whence it is manifeſt, That thoſe Songs, and that Melody, which the Saints and Children of God are to be ſound in the practice of, are to ſpring and ariſe from that which is pure and holy; therefore it is to be obſerv'd, that he tells them of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing filled with the Spirit, and of the Word of Chriſt dwelling richly in them, before he mentions Singing, or making Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the Lord; and alſo the ſame Apoſtle gives an account what he himſelf will do upon this account, ſaying, <hi>I will ſing with the Spirit, and I will ſing with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.15.</p>
               <p>As for the Songs of wicked, vain and ungodly People, who daily rebel againſt the Light and Spirit of the Lord, and the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:30541:51"/>pure motions and conceptions thereof in themſelves; we do no where find that ſuch have ever obtain'd divine acceptance, in their excerciſe therein, whilſt they have continued in Vanity and Wickedneſs, for the Lord by his Servants hath ſtill teſtified againſt them: Concerning <hi>Iſrael</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Take thou away from me the noiſe of thy Songs, for I will not hear the melody of thy Viols,</hi> Amos 5.23. Alſo, <hi>I will turn your Feaſts into Mourning, and all your Songs into Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> Amos 8.10. And of <hi>Tyrus</hi> he ſaith, <hi>I will cauſe the noiſe of thy Songs to ceaſe, and the ſound of thy Harps ſhall no more be heard,</hi> Ezek. 26.13. And what was the reaſon of all this? Even <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Iniquity,</hi> for that has always been the cauſe of Diſ-union and Separation between God and man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Its probable ſome may alledge the ſaying of the Apoſtle <hi>James, Is any among you Afflicted? let him Pray. Is any Merry? let him ſing Pſalmes.</hi> And would infer from thence, <hi>That if any be inclin'd to Mirth they may Sing by the Apoſtles Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In anſwer thereunto I ſay, That there are two ſorts of Mirth: The one is a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:30541:51"/>Mirth or Joy that ſprings up in the Hearts and Souls of Gods People, being touch't and overcome with the Love and Preſence of God, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>In thy Preſence is fullneſs of Joy; at thy right hand are Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 16.11. Alſo in <hi>Iſaiah, Behold my Servants ſhall ſing for joy of Heart,</hi> Iſa. 65.14. And <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>I will ſee you again, and your Hearts ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and your Joy no man taketh from you;</hi> John 16.22.</p>
               <p>The other ſort of Mirth or Joy is the Joy of wicked and ſinful Men, or that Mirth which ariſes from a vain, fooliſh and wanton Mind. The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> is ſo far from directing ſuch to ſing Pſalms, that in the ſame Epiſtle he tells them of Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Heavineſs, ſaying, <hi>Cleanſe your Hands ye Sinners, and purifie your Hearts ye double minded; be Afflisted and Mourn; let your Laughter be turned into Mourning, and your Joy into Heavineſs,</hi> James 4.8, 9. Alſo <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpoke of this Mirth and ſaid, <hi>In Laughter the Heart is ſorrowfull, and the end of that Mirth is heavineſs,</hi> Prov. 14.13. Again he ſaith, <hi>The Heart of Fools is in the Houſe of Mirth,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.4. Alſo the Prophet ſpeaking concerning <hi>Iſrael</hi> that was Apoſtatized and gone from the Lord,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:30541:52"/>and the counſel of his Spirit, amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things ſays, <hi>I will alſo cauſe her mirth to ceaſe,</hi> Hoſea 2.11. Thus then as it is manifeſt, that there is two ſorts of Mirth or Joy, and that the Mirth or Joy of the Wicked is but Vanity; therefore we may conclude, that the Mirth ſpoken of by the Apoſtle, was that true Mirth or Joy that ariſes in the Hearts of Gods People, being ſecretly toucht and overcome with the Love and Goodneſs of God, and thoſe who are witneſſes of this true Mirth and Joy, may ſing Pſalms according to the Apoſtles directions upon that account.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object,</hi> Some may object and ſay, <hi>That although the Lord diſowns vain Mirth, yet</hi> David<hi>'s Pſalmes are very good and uſeful, and may be ſung by thoſe profeſſing Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Although <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalmes are very good and uſeful, yet it does not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow that any can ſing them accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, unleſs they be in ſome meaſure endued with that Spirit of God <hi>David</hi> was endued with, and be under the fence and exerciſe of what they ſpeak: It is not only the repeating or ſinging over of good Words
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:30541:52"/>that the Lord looks at, (as hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſerv'd) but it is the frame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of their Souls and Spirits, from whom thoſe words do actually proceed: There's no queſtion but the Singers of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could expreſs themſelves with great Curioſity, and draw out their Notes very exactly; but what ſignified all that, ſo long as it was not real, but only formal, and that their Hearts were adulterated from the Lord? To what purpoſe can any rationally ſuppoſe it to be for People to ſing <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalmes in <hi>Saul</hi>'s Spirit? or for thoſe who ſpend their precious time in Wickedneſs, Folly and Vanity (and do very ſeldom think of Divine and Spiritual matters, or of the Eternal and Irrevocable decree that muſt in one day be paſt upon them) to ſing thus; <hi>I am weary with my Groanings. All the Night make I my Bed to Swim. I water my Couch with Tears. My Heart is like Wax, it is melted in the midſt of my Bowels. My Heart is not haughty, nor my Eyes lofty. My Soul is even as a weaned Child. I have hated the Congregation of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v l-Doers, and will not ſit with the Wicked. I have ſet the Lord always before me. My Heart is endicting a good matter. I have remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered thy Name, O Lord, and have kept thy
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:30541:53"/>Law. Thy Statutes have been my Songs in the Houſe of my Pilgrimage. Thy Teſtimonies have I taken as an heritage for ever, for they are the rejoycing of my Heart. Lord I have loved the habitation of thy Houſe, and the place where thine Honour dwelleth.</hi> Theſe were <hi>David</hi>'s Words, and its very likely that he was a Witneſs of what he ſpoke in theſe reſpects; but then for any to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to ſing them before the Lord, becauſe <hi>David</hi> ſpoke them, and not becauſe they are witneſſes of ſuch things in themſelves, nor of the Work and Influence of the Grace and Spirit of Chriſt, by which theſe things are effected; ſuch Singers will not meet with divine acceptance in ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, nor is Singing in the leaſt ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their State and Condition, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mourning and Lamentation becauſe of Sin and Tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <p>Howbeit ſtill, although the Songs of the Wicked ſhall be turn'd into Lamentation, and their Mirth into Heavineſs in one day, (if they report not) yet the Righteous ſhall Rejoyce and be exceeding Glad in the Lord, and ſhall ſing to his Praiſe and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in the Congregations of his People; as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Sing unto the Lord (O ye Saints of his) and give thanks at the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:30541:53"/>of his Holineſs,</hi> Pſal. 30.4. Again, <hi>Sing unto the Lord a new Song, and his Praiſe in the Congregation of Saints,</hi> Pſal. 149. 1. Its only thoſe who by the Power and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt are gathered and redeemed out of the Defilements and Vanities of this World, that can truly ſing this new Song, as <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>No man could learn that Song, but the hundred and fourty four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand which were redeemed from the Earth,</hi> Rev. 14.3. Such can ſing the Songs of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the Songs of Deliverance in the Land of the Living, and can truly Magnifie and Extol that great and powerful Name by which they have known Salvation.</p>
               <p>As for artificial Muſick although it was practized in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, yet we do neither find any Precept or Preſident for it in the writings of the new Teſtament: We read that <hi>David</hi> had Singers, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed men to make uſe of Muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (yea &amp; ſometimes made uſe thereof himſelf) yet we have cauſe to believe that what he appointed to be done upon theſe accounts, was not intended by him for gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying vain, fooliſh and wanton Minds, but the more to influence and affect the People, at that time, with that Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, and to ſing Praiſes to his holy
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:30541:54"/>Name; therefore ſays he, <hi>Awake, up my Glory, awake Pſaltery and Harp; I my ſelf will awake early. I will praiſe thee, O Lord, among the People; I will ſing unto thee among the Nations,</hi> Pſal. 57.8, 9. Again, <hi>Make a joyful noiſe unto God all ye Lands, ſing forth the honour of his Name, make his Praiſe Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,</hi> Pſal 66.1, 2.</p>
               <p>But then, although <hi>David</hi>'s intent might be good in making uſe of thoſe Muſical Inſtruments at that time, yet we read that when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was departed from the Lord, and the Counſel of his Spirit, and made uſe of thoſe things in a Formal and Cuſtomary way, the Lord declared againſt them ſaying, <hi>Take thou away from me the noiſe of thy Songs, for I will not hear the melody of thy Viols,</hi> Amos 5.23. And again, <hi>Wo to them that are at eaſe in</hi> Sion, <hi>and truſt in the Mountain of</hi> Samaria— <hi>That Chant to the ſound of the Viol, and invent to themſelves Inſtruments of Muſick like</hi> David: <hi>That drink Wine in Bowles, and anoint themſelves with the chiefeſt Oyntments, but they are not grieved for the Afflictions of</hi> Joſeph, Amos 6.1, 5, 6. From whence it is manifeſt, That it was then ſo far from being acceptable unto God, for Vain, Wicked and Sinful men to Chant to the ſound of the Viol,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:30541:54"/>and to invent unto themſelves Inſtruments of Muſick like <hi>David,</hi> that the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares he will not hear their melody, and alſo pronounces a Wo againſt them that are in the practice of ſuch things; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it was ſo then that the Lord was pleaſed to declare and teſtifie againſt the Songs and Melody of the <hi>Jews,</hi> under that Diſpenſation; it certainly behoves thoſe who are called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſeriouſly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what ground there is in true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity for the uſe of artificial Muſick upon any account whatſoever, and eſpecially in the performance of their Devotions to God Almighty; for as hath been before obſerv'd, we do no where find that either Chriſt or his Apoſtles did at any time ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther command or recommend any ſuch thing to be uſed among <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> not does it in the leaſt appear that the practice thereof is any way conſiſtant with the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Spirituality of that Religion and Worſhip which was Inſtituted by our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord, and Practized by his Diſciples and Followers in the primitive times.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:30541:55"/>
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>SInce then it is clearly manifeſt, by what hath been ſaid, that it is the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by his Grace and Spirit, that is (and ought to be) the chief and principal mover and actor in the Hearts and Souls of his People, in order to call and gather them out of the Vanities and Pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this preſent World, and to fit, prepare and qualife them for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming that pure and ſpiritual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service which is acceptable unto God in this Goſpel day, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in publick Preaching, Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Declarations, or in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Praiſes and Thankſgivings unto him; and that all men in their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and unconverted State (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding human Abilities) until they be converted to God, and have the help <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:30541:55"/>all ſuch undertakings, ſhall certainly feel and witneſs the returns of Divine Love, Life, Peace and Satisfaction, from the hand of the Lord, unto their Immortal Souls; and ſhall be ſecretly uphelp, ſupplied and ſupported by the bleſſed and holy power of God in all Straits and Difficulties that ſhall attend them upon the account of their ſervice to God and his Truth, and ſhall alſo be enabled, thereby, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſever in Faith and Patience unto the end of their Courſe, until ſuch time as it ſhall pleaſe the Lord God, of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Glory, to call, gather and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them hence into an heavenly Habitation of Reſt and Peace, with him forever: So that when the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Rebellious ſhall be ſeized upon with perpetual Sorrow and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, thoſe who have thus received the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and by his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and powerful hand have been conducted to their Eternal Manſion, ſhall together with all the Saints and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:30541:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>Children of God, that are gone before them, Everlaſtingly Praiſe, Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and Adore the Divine Majeſty, who alone is worthy of all Honour, Glory, Praiſe, Magnitude and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, at this time, henceforth and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERATA.</head>
            <p>In the Title Page, line 12. read <hi>revealed in men,</hi> in the Preface page 2. line 4. for <hi>Religions,</hi> read <hi>Religious.</hi> p. 4. l. 3. f. <hi>anology,</hi> r. <hi>anology.</hi> p. 5. l. 13. f. <hi>ſaw the,</hi> r. <hi>ſaw that the.</hi> p. 17. l. 14. f. <hi>hollow,</hi> r. <hi>hallow.</hi> p. 20. l. 2. f. <hi>meet,</hi> r. <hi>met.</hi> p. 38. l. 18. f. <hi>ſilent,</hi> r. in <hi>ſilence.</hi> p. 43. lines 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>not to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alick Letter.</hi> p. 51. l. 2. dele <hi>unto.</hi> p. 59. l. 18. f. <hi>intened,</hi> r. <hi>intended.</hi> p. 68. l. 16. f. <hi>feed, r. fed.</hi> l. 25. f. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> r. <hi>Chriſt's.</hi> p. 88. l. 11. f. <hi>God,</hi> r. <hi>Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30541:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
